<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Religion the perfection of man by John Jeffery ...</title>
            <author>Jeffery, John, 1647-1720.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 123 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 40 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A46709</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J518</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1467</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12887102</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12887102</idno>
            <idno type="VID">95039</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A46709)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 95039)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 386:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Religion the perfection of man by John Jeffery ...</title>
                  <author>Jeffery, John, 1647-1720.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 50 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Walter Kettilby ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: filmed from last page to beginning.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Perfection --  Religious aspects --  Christianity.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:95039:1"/>
            <p>Imprimatur, Liber cui Titulus, <hi>[The Abſolute Impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility of Tranſubſtantiation Demonſtrated.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Maij</hi> 3. 1688.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Guil. Needham</hi> RR. in Chriſto P. ac D. D. <hi>Wilhelmo</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiep. <hi>Cant.</hi> a Sacr. Dom.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:95039:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Abſolute Impoſſibility OF <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> DEMONSTRATED.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>William Rogers,</hi> at the <hi>Sun</hi> over-againſt St. <hi>Dunſtan</hi>'s Church in <hi>Fleetſtreet.</hi> MDCLXXXVIII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:95039:2"/>
            <pb n="i" facs="tcp:95039:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>UPON a careful Review of this enſuing Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, I find no cauſe to make any abatement from the Title of it, which promiſes to the Reader no leſs than ſtrict Demonſtration. If any of the following Arguments ſhould happen to fall ſhort of theſe pretenſions to the higheſt and cleareſt ſort of Proof that can be, it is wholly My fault, and I will mend it upon the firſt Notice of it. For I am ſure that the Subject-matter is capable of the moſt rigorous Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that ever was; and it has always been held, That the Eſſential Properties and Affections of a Body, ſuch as Quantity, Figure, and its relation to Place, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are the Proper Subject of Demonſtration. And let me here add, That ſuch a Doctrine as <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is, nor can be, a Matter of Revelation.</p>
            <p>For Scripture was given us, Either (1ſt) to Reveal things which were unknown to us by Natural Light: Such as the manner of the Creation of the World, and the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and more amazing Secret of the Redemption of it, wherein all Heaven was engaged; the Father ſent the Son, and the Son afterwards ſent the Holy Ghoſt; upon which occaſion we have a clear and manifeſt declaration of that Doctrine, which is commonly called the Trinity of Perſons in the Godhead, which was not ſo expreſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, under the Old Teſtament. To theſe may be added,
<pb n="ii" facs="tcp:95039:3"/>the aſſurance which is given us of a Reſurrection, and of a future Judgment, and of the different portion of good and bad men; of the one in Happineſs with all the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Company of Heaven, and of the other in Eternal Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments prepared for the Devil and his Angels. Now theſe are things which were <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndiſcoverable by Natural Light; but being Revealed, are very agreeable to it, and in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe contradict it.</p>
            <p>Or (2dly) To furniſh us with an Hiſtory of Providence, and of God's government of the World: Wherein moſt of the Divine Attributes are viſibly diſplayed. His Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs and Juſtice are to be ſeen in his Judgments, his Mercy in Deliverances, his Power in Miracles; his Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg, Faithfulneſs and Truth, in Propheſies; and the like. Now this part of Scripture does only clear up and exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plify our Natural Knowledg of God; and our Reaſon is ſo far from being diſtreſſed, that it is very much ſtrengthened and confirmed by it: As, to compare great things with ſmall, the Grammar Rule is proved and confirmed by the Example.</p>
            <p>Or (3dly) It was given us to improve our Natural Notices, and inforce our Natural Obligations to thoſe Duties, which we owe to God, our Neighbour, and our ſelves. And here our Reaſon triumphs, and is made perfect.</p>
            <p>Or (4thly) To eſtabliſh certain Religious Ordinances and Inſtitutions; ſuch as are the Sacraments, Religious Aſſemblies, Preaching, and the like: which our very Reaſon d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es ſubſcribe and approve as wiſe and holy Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointments, and as highly Inſtrumental to a good Life.</p>
            <p>Now theſe are matters worthy of God, and ſuch as all the Wiſdom in the World would expect ſhould be the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of a Divine Revelation. If God ſhould vouchſafe to make new Diſcoveries to the World, a man would look
<pb n="iii" facs="tcp:95039:3"/>for ſomewhat of this nature, which ſhould improve us, and ſupply the defects of Humane <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, and tend to the perfecting of our Nature. But no man would expect, that God ſhould ſend after us from Heaven to unteach us all that ever he had taught us in the day of our Creation, and to bleſs us with ſuch Diſcoveries as theſe. That the ſame Body is in the ſame Place, and is not in the ſame Place at the ſame time. That the Duration of <hi>24</hi> Hours is the Duration of <hi>1688</hi> Years. That a Miles Diſtance, and the Diſtance of <hi>10000</hi> Miles is Equal. That the ſame thing may Exiſt and not Exiſt at once. That the ſelf-ſame ſingle thing may have two con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Natures at the ſame time, and not be what it is; together with the reſt of the Myſteries of <hi>Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation.</hi> We are ſure that a Divine Revelation cannot contradict the Common Senſe and Reaſon of Mankind; for that would be to pronounce them <hi>Falſe Witneſſes of God,</hi> when by theſe alone we know that there is a God, and are led to the diſcovery of his Eternal Power and Godhead; which muſt be known before we can think of Revelation. For it is in vain to talk of the Word of God, till we know that there is a God whoſe Word this Revelation is. In ſhort, If any ſuppoſed Revelation ſhould contradict the plain Principles of Reaſon, it would be the ſame thing, or rather worſe, than if that Revelation ſhould contradict it ſelf. For if a Revelation ſhould contradict it ſelf, we could not indeed receive it upon thoſe terms, becauſe we ſhould be bound to believe it and disbelieve it at once, and therefore we could not believe it at all; But if this Revelation ſhould contradict the plain Principles of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, then it would overthrow that <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding which we are ſure we received from the hands of God: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if we ſhould renounce our Reaſon to believe ſuch a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation, we muſt in that caſe part with a Certainty for
<pb n="iv" facs="tcp:95039:4"/>an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncertainty. For we cannot know (unleſs we will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it blindfold, and then we know nothing) That ever any Revelation came from God, till our Reaſon has made it out to us that it did: And therefore to abandon our Reaſon for the ſake of any Revelation, is to make our ſelves ſurer of the thing proved, than of the Proof it ſelf, which is very abſurd; for that which makes us certain of another thing, muſt needs be firſt and beſt known to us.</p>
            <p>I ſhould not have put ſuch a Caſe as this, for it is an impoſſible Caſe, but that the <hi>Papiſts</hi> themſelves have put it, and have decided it the wrong way, and have made <hi>Axiomes</hi> and ſelf-evident Principles out of the falſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination of it. So <hi>Cartes</hi> concludes his Firſt Book of <hi>Principles;</hi> 
               <q>That we must fix this in our minds as the chief and principal Rule, That thoſe things which are revealed to us by God, are to be believed as the most certain of all others: And altho perchance the most clear and evident Light of Reaſon that can be, ſhould ſeem to ſuggest to us the contrary, yet we must believe Divine Authority alone, rather than our own Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</q> Now this I ſay is an impoſſible Caſe; for we have not a more clear and evident proof, than the most clear and most evident Light of Reaſon that can be, Ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that God has revealed any one Doctrine in particular, Or made any Revelation at all, Or that there is a God. And therefore if any revealed Doctrine in particular can be ſuppoſed to contradict the most clear and and most evident Light of Reaſon that can be, ſo that it ought to be ſet aſide, and disbelieved as Falſe; Then that Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine does therein overthrow both its own Credit, and the belief of a Revelation in general, and even of a Deity: And conſequently it is, as I ſaid, an Impoſſible Caſe, and a perfect Inconſistency; for at once it ſuppoſes the belief of a Divine Revelation, and yet destroys the belief of any ſuch thing.</p>
            <pb n="v" facs="tcp:95039:4"/>
            <p>The Gentlemen of the Port Royal, in their Logick or Art of Thinking, have advanced this Rule of <hi>Cartes</hi> to the ſtate and degree of an Axiome, or undoubted Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: For in <hi>Part 4. Chap. 7.</hi> they make this, together with two other Axiomes which uſher it in, to be the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of Faith. I ſhall conſider them all three.</p>
            <p>
               <label>AXIOME <hi>VIII.</hi>
               </label>
               <hi>A Man ought not to deny that which is clear and evident, for not being able to comprehend that which is obſcure.</hi> This is but a lame Axiome; for tho it be Truth, yet it is not the whole Truth in this matter: For a Man ought not to deny that which is clear and evident upon any account whatſoever. He ought not to go againſt known Truth, (for that is the Engliſh of what is clear and evident) for the ſake of any thing, either known or unknown.</p>
            <p>
               <label>AXIOME <hi>IX.</hi>
               </label>
               <hi>It is of the nature of a Finite mind, not to be able to comprehend that which is Infinite.</hi> This is an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted Truth, and no man can gainſay it; only it has the misfortune to be found here in bad company, and to be applied to falſe purpoſes, as we ſhall ſee by and by.</p>
            <p>
               <label>AXIOME <hi>X.</hi>
               </label>
               <hi>The Teſtimony of a Perſon infinitely powerful, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely wiſe, infinitely good, and infinitely true, ought to have more force to perſuade our Minds, than the moſt convincing Reaſons.</hi> But I ask again, Have we any more, than the moſt convincing Reaſons, to
<pb n="vi" facs="tcp:95039:5"/>perſuade us that there is any ſuch Perſon thus qualified? Or that this Infinitely Credible and Adorable Being has given any Teſtimony at all? If not, Then I ſay, that this Axiome is an Inconſiſtency, it ſupplants it ſelf, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermines the very ground on which it ſtands. That muſt needs be a very tottering and ruinous foundation of Faith, which is eſtabliſhed upon a contrariety and oppoſition to the Moſt Convincing Reaſons: But an abſurd Religion may be glad of ſuch Axiomes as it can get, and muſt be content to be ſerved with an abſurd Logic.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Meſſieurs</hi> promiſe us here to ſay ſomewhat more of Faith afterwards, which accordingly they do, <hi>Chap. 11.</hi> and therefore thither we will follow them, and ſee how they apply theſe <hi>Axiomes</hi> to eſtabliſh <hi>Tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> Where firſt they inculcate their former <hi>Axiome</hi> in thoſe words, <q>
                  <hi>Il eſt certain, &amp;c.</hi> It is certain that Divine Faith ought to have more power over our Minds, than our own Reaſon. And this is certain, even by Reaſon it ſelf, which ſhews us, that we ought always to prefer that which is more certain, before that which is leſs certain; and that it is more certain that what God ſays is true, than what our Reaſon perſuades us; becauſe God is more uncapable of Deceiving us, than our Reaſon of being Deceived.</q> Now, if what Reaſon perſuades us be not certain, when, for inſtance, it perſuades us that there is a God, then there is no poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible certainty of a Revelation, which ſhall ſtand in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition with Reaſon, and be preferred before it. And therefore this is the the old Enchantment over again, which perfectly turns the Reaſon of Mankind into a Stone, ſo that it cannot move one ſtep either forward or back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. For if the moſt clear and evident light of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that can be, (as <hi>Cartes</hi>'s word is), if the moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing Reaſons (as the Port-Royal word is) may be
<pb n="vii" facs="tcp:95039:5"/>falſe, Then it is impoſſible for us to know any thing: Nay, it is impoſſible for us ſo much as to know, that we know nothing.</p>
            <p>But in the very next words they relent, and tell us quite another ſtory. <q>
                  <hi>Neanmoins a conſiderer, &amp;c.</hi> Nevertheleſs to conſider things exactly, that which we evidently perceive, both by Reaſon, or by the faithful report of our Senſes, is never contrary to that which Divine Faith teaches us. But that which makes us believe ſo, is, that we take no heed where it is that the evidence of our Reaſon and of our Senſes ought to ſtop, and to go no further.</q> Methinks men ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider things exactly, before they lay down Axiomes and firſt Principles, and not after: For now it ſeems that Revelation is never contrary to the evidence of Reaſon, or the faithful report of our Senſes, (for if they are never contrary to that, then that is never contrary to them) and therefore the oppoſition which was ſuppoſed to be betwixt them, and the renouncing of Reaſon, and cleaving to Faith, which followed thereupon, proves to be wholly a miſtake. So that they have plainly given up their 10th Axiome for Nonſenſe; and now they are up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a new queſtion, which is concerning the juſt bounds and full extent of Senſe and Reaſon, and to ſhew how ſhort ſighted they both are, in diſcerning a bit of Bread.</p>
            <p>Their next words are theſe: <q>
                  <hi>Par exemple, &amp;c.</hi> For Example, Our Senſes ſhew us clearly in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament ſome roundneſs and whiteneſs; but our Senſes do not teach us whether it be the ſubſtance of Bread which cauſes our eyes to perceive this Roundneſs and Whiteneſs: And thus Faith is not contrary to the evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of our Senſes, when it tells us, that this is not the ſubſtance of Bread, which is aboliſhed, having
<pb n="viii" facs="tcp:95039:6"/>been changed into the Body of Jeſus Chriſt by the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> and that we ſee nothing more than the ſpecies and appearances of Bread which ſtill remain, although the ſubſtance be aboliſhed, and be no more.</q> When the <hi>Papiſts</hi> are diſpoſed to make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves merry with the follies of us poor Hereticks, there is no ſuch happy ſubject of their Drollery as this, That we pretend to ſee Subſtances, and have ſuch exquiſite Senſes as will penetrate farther and deeper than all other mens. Now on the other hand we can tell them very ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly, that we never ſaw Roundneſs or Whiteneſs in our lives, nor can any of our Senſes ſhew us any ſuch rarities: We cannot deny but that we have ſeen Round and White Subſtances or Bodies, or pieces of Matter, call them what you will; but as for Roundneſs and Whiteneſs, we believe them to be objects ſo dazling, that they would certainly blind us. The roundneſs, and whiteneſs, and ſweetneſs which they ſee and taſt in the Sacrament without a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, are the round, and white, and ſweet nothings which we never yet ſaw nor taſted, tho we ſometimes promiſe them to our Children for Fairings: But Subſtances we continually ſee, and cannot look beſide them: For every thing which is ſeen, heard, ſmelt, taſted, or felt, is a Subſtance, and which is more, it is a groſs material Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, or elſe it could not affect and make an impreſſion upon ſuch groſs material organs of Senſe as ours are. What is it that ſo feelingly moves our Senſes, and reſiſts our Touch, but a Body or Material Subſtance? For Ten thouſand Roundneſſes and Whiteneſſes will not make up One object of Senſe. And as for the inſtance which lies before us, of a piece of Bread, it is a Subſtance the moſt familiar, and the beſt-known to us of all others. We can ſee, and taſte, and feel, and ſmell it, and know it blindfold. And not only we, but moſt of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures
<pb n="ix" facs="tcp:95039:6"/>about us can ſee, and taſte, and ſmell the Subſtance of Bread as well as we, and know it very diſtinctly, and will ſingle it out from twenty other Round and White Subſtances whatſoever. And their Senſes were certainly given them to diſcern Subſtances, and not Accidents, for otherwiſe a round and white Stone, or a round and white Chip, would ſerve their turn as well; but Figure and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour are not their buſineſs, but a Subſtance, which will nouriſh them, and which will be altered and aſſimilated into the ſubſtance of Fleſh and Blood. And therefore whether the ſubſtance of a Wafer be Bread, or whether it be a Human Body, I will refer it wholly to all the Animals in the World, which love Bread, and will not ſeize upon a living Man; for they are competent and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different judges in this matter: Always excepting thoſe Animals which are the Maſters of <hi>The School of the Euchariſt;</hi> for they are all Parties and Bigots, and eſpecially the Dog of <hi>Lisbon.</hi> In ſhort, I challenge all the World to tell me, what there is belonging to the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Bread, which we do not ſee and diſcern by our ſenſes, and which is not faithfully reported to us by them. And therefore when our ſenſes evidently ſhew us, that a Wafer is the ſubſtance of Bread, and on the other hand, the Popiſh Faith teaches us that it is not the ſubſtance of Bread, but the ſubſtance of a Human Body, <hi>That Faith</hi> is plainly contrary to the evidence of our Senſes; which becauſe the <hi>Meſſieurs</hi> ſaid before, Divine Faith Never is, it leaves their Faith under a different cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter from that which is Divine.</p>
            <p>They proceed in the following words, <q>
                  <hi>Noſtre raiſon de meſme, &amp;c.</hi> Our Reaſon in like manner ſhews us that one ſingle Body is not at the ſame time in divers places, nor two Bodies in one and the ſame place; but
<pb n="x" facs="tcp:95039:7"/>this ought to be underſtood of the natural condition of Bodies, becauſe it would be a defect of Reaſon for a Man to imagine that our Mind, being Finite, is able to comprehend how far the Infinite Power of God reaches. And therefore when Hereticks, in order to deſtroy the Myſteries of Faith, as the Trinity, Incarnation and Euchariſt, do object thoſe Pretended Impoſſibilities which they draw from Reaſon, in this very thing they themſelves do viſibly depart from Reaſon, in pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be able to Comprehend in their Finite Mind the Infinite extent of the Power of God.</q>
            </p>
            <p>In this ſhort paſſage there are many things liable to exception. For (1ſt,) Our Reaſon does not only ſhew us, that one ſingle Body <hi>is not</hi> at the ſame time in divers Places, but it ſhews us alſo that it <hi>cannot be</hi> in divers Places at once, for this reaſon, becauſe in that caſe one ſingle Body would be divers Bodies, which is a Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction. And therefore (2ly,) The Limitation which follows, is falſe, That this ought to be underſtood of the Natural Condition of Bodies, and reſtrained only to that. For whether Bodies be in a Natural condition, or Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural, one ſingle Body cannot be divers Bodies at the ſame time, for then it is no longer one ſingle Body. No Supernatural caſe or condition can make a Contradiction to be true. For inſtance, St. <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> told the <hi>Jews</hi> that God was able of thoſe Stones, which lay upon the Banks of <hi>Jordan,</hi> to raiſe up Children unto <hi>Abraham.</hi> In their Natural condition they were Stones, but in this Supernatural condition they would have been Men; but in no condition was it poſſible for them to be both Stones and Men at the ſame time, becauſe it is a Repugnancy. For to ſay, a Stone is a Man, is to ſay a Stone is not a Stone, that is to ſay, it is not, or it is nothing at all,
<pb n="xi" facs="tcp:95039:7"/>which I hope no Man will ſay is the work of an Infinite Power. And therefore (3ly,) in ſaying That One Body cannot be in divers places at once, we do not thereby imagine that a Finite Mind can comprehend how far the Infinite Power of God reaches; This is both a falſe charge, and a falſe inference. For what has Omnipotency to do with Nothing? To effect Nothing, is a derogation to all Power, much more is it beneath that which is Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite. When therefore we vindicate the Divine Power, and aſſert the Infinity of it, and ſay it is removed at the greateſt diſtance from all defect, Is this to ſay that a Finite mind can comprehend it? No; God forbid that our heads ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ld be filled with ſuch croſs Popiſh Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions, as to ſay, that every Contradiction is Impoſſible, and yet this Contradiction is Poſſible; That a Finite may hold an Infinite, and that the Greater may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by the Leſs. We admire and adore the Infinite Power of God, and we are ſenſible of it every Minute, for in Him we live and move and have our Being, and yet we do not comprehend it; neither have we the leaſt thought or imagination of Comprehending it; for we know that this is utterly Inconſiſtent with the neceſſary Imperfection and Limitation of a Creature ſtate. The Infinite Power of God ſtands like a Great Mountain. Now we can ſee a great Mountain only by parts, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not view it all round at once, much leſs can we graſp or comprehend it, and take it up in our Arms. But yet as we know and ſee, that this incomprehenſible Mountain (which is an Object too big for our Senſes) is not a Valley; ſo we are full as ſure that Perfection is not Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection, and that Infinite Power (tho we never pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to meaſure the extent of it) is free from all Impotency, and cannot atchieve Impoſſibilities and No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>things.
<pb n="xii" facs="tcp:95039:8"/>As we know by his Neceſſary Exiſtence that God cannot ceaſe to Be, and by his Infinite Wiſdom that he cannot Err, and by his Infinite Truth that it is Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for God to Lye: So we are aſſured by his Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Power that he cannot make a Contradiction, a No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, an Inconſiſtency, which is always unmade again as faſt as it is made. If God ſhould Create and Annihi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late a thing at once, he would plainly effect neither, and nothing would follow upon ſuch an Impoſſible Act. (4thly,) The <hi>Meſſieurs</hi> inſinuate, as if the Impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities which are brought againſt <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> were of the ſame ſort, and as Falſe and Pretended, as thoſe which are objected againſt the Tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ty, and the Incarnation of our Saviour; but I ſhall leave that to the judgment of every indifferent Reader, after he has weighed and conſidered the following Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>And thus I have at leaſt ſhaken thoſe Axiomes, which were purpoſely erected as Strongholds, to cover and ſhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the abſurd Doctrines of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially that of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> by feigning that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation and Reaſon are at variance, and that in that Caſe Reaſon is to be abandoned. It may juſtly be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired that <hi>Cartes,</hi> a Man of clear Senſe, ſhould begin ſuch Rules; but it is to be remembred, That he was to make ſome amends for the bold Truths he had elſewhere delivered; and likewiſe, That he was able to comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as well as he did particular Perſons, without being a Slave to his Complement: for when he was preſſed with what he had ſaid upon ſuch Occaſions, and with his own very words; he uſed to tell them, <hi>Urbanitas Styli Gallici te fefellit,</hi> you did not underſtand a French Complement. I doubt not but the Learned Men of the Port Royal did very well under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand
<pb n="xiii" facs="tcp:95039:8"/>it; but it is their Craft to make ſilver Shrines for <hi>Diana;</hi> and all the Commendation we can give them, is to ſay, that they are very able Workmen, and Maſters of their Trade, ſuch a one as it is.</p>
            <p>To conclude, Reaſon is that whereby we chuſe our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and judg whether it be a Revelation which came from God, and whereby we diſtinguiſh betwixt the Bible and the Alchoran. And, as <hi>Cartes</hi> ſays,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Preſp ad 2. Obj. Art. 5.</hi>
               </note> If a Turk or a Heathen, being induced by ſome Falſe Reaſonings, ſhould embrace Chriſtianity, and did not know that it came from God, he would not thereupon be a Chriſtian, but rather he would be guilty of a Sin, in not uſing his Reaſon aright. Reaſon is that whereby we interpret a Revelation; or elſe a man can give no reaſon why he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprets it in that manner, rather than in another. And as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks in another Caſe, <hi>Do ye not know that the Saints ſhall judg the World?</hi> &amp;c. Do ye not know that Reaſon muſt judg of the Sum of Religion? And if the whole muſt be judged by it, Is it unworthy to judg in the ſmalleſt Matters, ſuch as a Phraſe, or a Figure? Shall it not judge in ſo plain and ſo eaſie a Caſe as this? That Chriſt's Body on which the Woman poured her Alabaſter Box of Ointment, <hi>Matth. 26.12.</hi> was his living Natural Body; And the Body which <hi>Joſeph</hi> of <hi>Arimathea</hi> begged and buried, <hi>Matth. 27.58.</hi> was his dead Natural Body; And the Body of Chriſt which is to be Edified, <hi>Eph. 4.12.</hi> is the Church, or Society of all Chriſtian People; And the Body of Chriſt which is to be eaten, <hi>Matth. 26.26.</hi> is the Sign, or Sacrament, or Memorial of his Body? If Reaſon may not judg in this Caſe, by conſidering and examining theſe ſeveral Places, but is to be ſet aſide or renounced, and the Letter of Scripture to determine it; Then I am ſure, that if the
<pb n="xiv" facs="tcp:95039:9"/>Communicant, by vertue of thoſe words, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> eats the Natural Body of Chriſt either dead or alive, At the ſame time he alſo eats up all Chriſtian People by vertue of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s words, who in like manner expreſly calls Them <hi>the Body of Chriſt.</hi> In a word, whatſoever is believed or done in Religion, muſt be by Reaſon, or elſe it is an Irrational Belief and Practice. For Reaſon is the Principle of a Man; and whatſoever is not done by it, is not done by the Man, it is not an Humane Act, but the Act of a Brute. Whenever there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I become a Scholar in the <hi>School of the Euchariſt,</hi> and renounce the Reaſon which God has given me, to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Doctrine of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> I am fully reſolved to keep a decorum in it, and I will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly go over to that Church upon all Four.</p>
            <p>I have not thus much inſiſted upon Reaſon, becauſe we are deſtitute of Scripture-proof, to ſhew that <hi>Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation</hi> is falſe; for we have not a clearer and ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler evidence from Revelation, that our Saviour came into the World, than we have that his Body, even ſince his Reſurrection, is ſuch, as cannot poſſibly be preſent in form of Bread. As to name no more, <hi>Luke 24.39. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold my hands and my feet, that it is I my ſelf: han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle me and ſee, for a Spirit hath not fleſh and bones, as ye ſee me have.</hi> Theſe are the Scripture-marks of our Saviour's Body, which he himſelf gave on purpoſe to know it by. But can we poſſibly behold Hands and Feet in a Wafer? Can we handle and ſee Fleſh and Bones in it? If we cannot, Then it is not He himſelf; otherwiſe theſe are fallacious Marks of him, for <hi>roundneſs and whiteneſs,</hi> and <hi>no Hands and Feet,</hi> and <hi>no Fleſh and Bones,</hi> might have been the Marks as well. But I was hereby willing to ſhew, that as Scripture is against
<pb n="xv" facs="tcp:95039:9"/>
               <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> ſo the primitive Light of Reaſon is against it too, the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nwritten as well as the Written Word of God: And that as <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> tends to the destruction of all that is Man or Christian in us; So on the other hand, Common Senſe, Reaſon, Christia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and all that is within us, does riſe up in oppoſition against ſo monstrous and miſchievous a Doctrine.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:95039:10"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:95039:10"/>
            <head>THE ABSOLUTE IMPOSSIBILITY OF <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> DEMONSTRATED.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>TRanſubstantiation</hi> is not the Name of one ſingle Abſurdity, but it ſignifies as <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> does, many Thouſands in one. For which reaſon it is very hard to draw them up, or put them into any good order, which however I ſhall endeavour to do under theſe two Heads:
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> Of <hi>Intellectual Abſurdities.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>And <hi>Secondly,</hi> Of <hi>Practical Abſurdities.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The firſt Head is of <hi>Intellectual Abſurdities;</hi> by which I mean ſuch Falſhoods as are repugnant to the common Reaſon and Underſtanding of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind. And I purpoſely wave all thoſe Abſurdities of <hi>Tranſubstantiation</hi> which contradict our Senſes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe if a man be bent upon it, and will outface me out of all all my ſenſes, as I cannot believe him, ſo I
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:95039:11"/>cannot diſprove him: If he ſays the Sun does not ſhine, when at the ſame time I am really dazled with the light and brightneſs of it, I can only ſay as I find, and appeal to his own ſenſes, and deſire him to do me right. In caſe a <hi>Romaniſt</hi> ſhould bear me down, that the Bible in my hand is not a Book, but the living Judg of Controverſie, Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the Eleventh, and all the Biſhops of the Chriſtian World ſitting together in Council; I can't help my ſelf: eſpecially if he pretend to have chang'd the Book into ſuch, and ſo many living men by ſaying ſome powerfully charming words over it; and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, if in condeſcenſion and compliance with the frailty of human ſenſe, he likewiſe acknowledges that it looks like a Printed and Bound Book, and is cloath'd with all the Accidents and Properties of a Book, and that one part of the Enchantment lies in this, that tho in all appearance it is a Book, yet it is in reality Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the Eleventh, and an Aſſembly of living Biſhops; in this caſe I can't uſe my ſenſes, becauſe he has already forecloſed the uſe and evidence of them. But if he goes on to tell me utter Impoſſibilities, and after having affirm'd to me that the two Epiſtles of St. <hi>Peter</hi> are nothing elſe but Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> in perſon; and that the very ſame Holy Father (whom I think I have in my hand at <hi>London</hi>) is alſo at the ſelf ſame time perſonally preſent at <hi>Rome,</hi> and at <hi>Paris,</hi> and at <hi>Vienna,</hi> and in ten thouſand other very remote places; he then puts me into a way to break the Enchantment, and to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw his Deluſion with ſuch Arguments, as will not be ſatisfied by ſaying, <hi>That the ſenſes may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, and cannot dive into the eſſence of things.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:95039:11"/>
            <p>It is not ſuch a light and ludicrous Cheat as this I have been now ſpeaking of, which the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> has put upon the World for many Ages toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; for then I queſtion, whether I ſhould ever have employed my Pen againſt it; (though it is an indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to mankind to impoſe upon them, to deceive and make children of them) but the <hi>Romiſh</hi> delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is of an higher nature, for it is the Cheat of a bit of Bread which you muſt believe to be a man's body, nay to be a God: And accordingly if you will not worſhip and bow down to this bit of Bread, and acknowledg it to be your Maker, then ſhall you be condemned for an <hi>Heretick;</hi> then will they zealouſly tell you, <hi>That they will no more pray for you,
<note place="margin">See the Book of Martyrs in Q. <hi>Maries</hi> Reign.</note> than they will for a Dog; and that as your Body fries in a Smithfield-Fire, ſo your Soul ſhall for ever burn in Hell.</hi> And therefore it is of as great conſequence to men, as their ſouls and bodies are worth, to know the truth of this matter; for which cauſe I earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intreat them to weigh and ponder the Arguments, and carefully to attend to the Demonſtrations, which I ſhall here lay down before them.</p>
            <p>To proceed with the more ſtrength and clearneſs in this matter, and to avoid needleſs Repetitions, and ſuch like incumbrances of a Diſcourſe, I ſhall here premiſe ſome very reaſonable Demands, which without any man's leave I ſhall take for granted: 1. That a Doctrine which conſiſts of Impoſſibilities, is an impoſſible Doctrine. 2. That Omnipotency it ſelf cannot make an Impoſſibility; for what can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be done at all, cannot be done by Almighty Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. Suppoſing an infinite exceſs of Power, (as we are ſure there is in God) yet it cannot do what can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:95039:12"/>be done. 3. That a Contradiction is an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibility.</p>
            <p>From theſe Premiſes I ſhall infer, That every Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction which is contained in the Doctrine of <hi>Tranſubstantiation,</hi> is an undoubted proof of the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibility of it; ſo that it never was, is, or can be be true, and that the pretence of Omnipotency it ſelf cannot ſupport it.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>To avoid the force of this and ſuch like Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations, the Repreſenter of Popery tells us, <q>That Chriſt gives to his Body a ſupernatural manner of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:95039:12"/>Exiſtence, by which being left without Extenſion of Parts, and rendred independent of Place, it may be one and the ſame in many Places at once, and whole in every part of the Symbols, and not obnoxious to any Corporeal Contingencies.</q> Thus far he. It may be, a few new-deviſed terms, and half a dozen Inconſiſtent Words contradictiouſly jumbled together, are able to overthrow a Demonſtration. We will try whether they can or no. As for the Privileges and Prerogatives of this Body (which it muſt always be carefully remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred is an Organized Human Body) to Exiſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Extenſion of Parts, to be whole in every part of the Symbols, and not to be obnoxious to any Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poreal Contingencies, they are Myſteries which will keep cold, and we ſhall conſider them by and by. The Thing to be thought of at preſent, is, <hi>A Supernatural manner of Exiſtence, whereby this Body is rendred independent of Place, and may be one and the ſame in many Places at once.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Body which exiſts in a Supernatural man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, muſt either, (1.) Be <hi>every where,</hi> and in all Places; which manner of Exiſtence is Immenſe and Infinite, and peculiar to God alone. It is a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Attribute; and where there is one Divine Attribute, there are all the reſt. But if by an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible Suppoſition, this manner of Exiſtence were Communicable to a Body, yet it would not ſerve their purpoſe; for then this Body would be in <hi>too many</hi> Places at once, in all other Places out of the Sacrament, as well as in it; and ſo there would be no need of Prieſts to make Chriſt's Body in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which would be a thing very inconvenient,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:95039:13"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:95039:13"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:95039:14"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:95039:14"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:95039:15"/>at leaſt for that Order of Men. Or elſe (2.) This Body which is Independent of Place, muſt be in <hi>no Place;</hi> and then with it's Supernatural manner of Exiſtence, it does not Exiſt at all; for that which is No-where, is nothing. Or (3dly and <hi>laſtly</hi>) It muſt be <hi>ſomewhere;</hi> for let the manner of Exiſtence be what it will, Natural, or Supernatural, or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite, ſtill this Body, which is independent of Place, muſt either be Every-where, or Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, or No-where; if this Body be <hi>Every-where,</hi> as was ſhewed before, it would be Infinite, which is Blaſphemy; for if a Body may have Divine Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes, and be a God, then God may be a Body. And then again, if this Body be <hi>No-where,</hi> it is Non-Exiſtent and Nothing. And therefore it remains that it be <hi>Some where:</hi> And this is eaſily granted; for it is ſaid to be in many Places at once, which is many Some-wheres. Well, if it may be in many Places at once, it may be in one of thoſe many Places: This is undeniable, and muſt be granted us. Let us make uſe therefore once again, of the former Scheme, and let this one Place be A, and D the Body in it; and now at laſt, though this Body D be independent of Place, yet we are ſure of it in one Place, for it is in A. But, it ſeems, it may be in ſeveral other places at the ſame time: Be it ſo, and let B and C be two of thoſe other Places, and let D be the ſelf-ſame independent Body in thoſe Places; and then we are haunted again with all the former Contradictions. D is in A, and at the ſame time D is not in A, for it is in B, which is not in A. Again, D is wholly in B, and D is wholly out of B at the ſame time, for it is in C,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:95039:15"/>which is wholly out of B. So that this pretended Supernatural manner of Exiſtence, is full of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions, that is to ſay, it is Impoſſible. Which was to be Demonſtrated.</p>
            <p>In this foregoing Demonſtration I have taken the word <hi>Place</hi> in the largeſt Senſe, ſo as to contain Angels and Spirits, who are <hi>Somewhere,</hi> and who cannot be <hi>Elſewhere</hi> at the ſame time. And this I did on purpoſe to ſhew, That though the Body of Chriſt ſhould be preſent after the manner of a Spirit, without filling a Place, or having any rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Dimenſions of it, (which was the old Hypotheſis, before the Repreſenter came with his new Jargon); and tho it took up no more room than a Thought does in a Man's Mind, yet it were impoſſible for it to be in many Places at once. So that if we ſhould grant Matter to be Immaterial, and a Body to be a Spirit, yet the Papiſts are ſo intangled in the Abſurdity of this Doctrine, that it would do them no good to allow them half a ſcore Contradictions, neither would it any way relieve them, or free them from the reſt. Whereas on the other hand, a Body is known to fill and poſſeſs the Place in which it is, and is circumſcribed by the bounds and limits of the Place, which is commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurate to the Magnitude and Figure of the Body: So that if a Body ſhould be in many Places at once, it might not only have quite contrary Situations, and be <hi>Eaſt, Weſt, North,</hi> and <hi>South</hi> of it ſelf, be above it ſelf, and below it ſelf all at once; but alſo it would be <hi>Circumſcribed</hi> and <hi>not Circumſcribed</hi> at the ſame time; which is a very plain and open Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:95039:16"/>
            <p n="2">2. The Second Head of Contradictions are thoſe which attend the Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation in point of <hi>Time.</hi> Every thing that has now a Being, either always had a Being, and is Eternal; which only God is; or elſe it had a beginning of its Being, in which it has continued ever ſince; which is the condition of all Creatures; and this Continuance of a Creature in Being we call the <hi>Duration</hi> of it, which is ſo eſſential to all Subſtances, whether Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial or Immaterial, that it is abſolutely inſeparable from them: For when their Being began, their Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration began; and when their Duration ceaſes, their Being ceaſes. This Duration is counted by Days, Months, and Years, and ſuch like greater or leſſer portions of Time, which <hi>Time</hi> is nothing elſe but the meaſure of Duration, whereby we reckon how long a Subſtance has continued or perſevered in Being. And now we have a Teſt in our hands, to try whether it be not abſolutely impoſſible for the Tranſubſtantiation-Body in the Sacrament to be the very Body of Chriſt, which was born of the Virgin <hi>Mary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Body which was born of the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> has continued in Being 1688 years; whereas the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy which the Prieſt
<note n="(2)" place="margin">Conficiunt Chriſti Corpus &amp; Sanguinem <hi>Catech. Trid.</hi> de Euch <hi>ſſ.</hi> 82. Edit. <hi>Lugdun.</hi> 1676.</note> made yeſterday, has conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued in Being but one Day; but the Duration of one Day only cannot be the Duration of 1688 years: And the Duration of 1688 years is now in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeparable from the Body of Chriſt born of the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin <hi>Mary,</hi> for the Duration of a Subſtance is inſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable from the Subſtance; therefore the Body which the Prieſt made yeſterday, cannot be the Body which was born of the Virgin <hi>Mary.</hi> Which was to be Demonſtrated.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:95039:16"/>
            <p>Again; If the Body in the Sacrament which was made, that is, began to be yeſterday, is the ſame Body which has continued 1688 Years, then the ſame Body continued 1687 Years, and upwards, before it began to be; but before it began to be, it was not in Being; and conſequently, in every Minute during that 1687 years, the ſame Body was in Being, and was not in Being. Which amounts to Millions of Contradictions.</p>
            <p>Once more. It muſt be granted, <hi>That the Cauſe is in Being before the Effect;</hi> and it would be a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Repugnancy to ſay the contrary; for then the Effect would be both before its ſelf, for it is not an Effect till it be Cauſed; and alſo before its Cauſe, and ſo would be Cauſed by that which is not. Now the Cauſes of the Tranſubſtantiation-Body are theſe amongſt others. 1. The Bread out of which it is produced; which is ſo neceſſary, that this Change cannot be wrought out of any other Subſtance in the World, Fleſh nor Fiſh, Pillar nor Poſt, nor any thing elſe that can be named; and therefore this is the neceſſary Matter of the Tranſubſtantiation-Body, or the Cauſe <hi>out of which</hi> it is made. 2ly, The Baker by whom the Bread was made; for he that is a Cauſe of the Cauſe, is a Cauſe of the thing Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. 3ly, The Marvellous Operator, the Prieſt, who makes the Body, together with his Intention. 4ly, Which ſeems to be an <hi>Instrumental</hi> Cauſe, his Pronouncing theſe words, <hi>Hoc enim eſt Corpus meum,</hi> in one Breath. 5ly, The Conſideration which moved him to ſay a Maſs at that time.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:95039:17"/>
            <p>But neither the Bread, nor the Baker, nor the Prieſt, nor his Intention, nor his Voice, nor his Breath, nor the Propoſal, ſuppoſe of Twelve pence, to him to ſay a Maſs; neither all nor any of theſe, which were the Cauſes of that Tranſubſtantiation Body, which was made yeſterday, and did contribute more or leſs to the producing of it; I ſay, none of theſe Cauſes were in Being an Hundred years ago; and if the Cauſes were not in Being, much leſs was the Effect in Being, otherwiſe the Effect muſt be before the Cauſe, which is impoſſible. But the Body of Chriſt, born of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> was in being 1600 Years ago, which is more than One hundred Years ago, and this is impoſſible for the Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation-Body which was made yeſterday; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is impoſſible for the Tranſubſtantiation-Body to be the Body of Chriſt born of the Virgin <hi>Mary. Q. E. D.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I wonder, that when the Repreſenter's hand was in, and he had made Chriſt's Body <hi>Independent of Place,</hi> he had not likewiſe made it <hi>Independent of Time,</hi> for that was full as neceſſary to be done as the other.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Third Head of Contradictions are thoſe which relate to <hi>Quantity;</hi> under which Head I was going to Demonſtrate, That the ſame Body cannot at the ſame time be Bigger and Leſs than it it ſelf; That it cannot be an Organized Human Body, Five Foot and an half long, and at the ſame time be ſtowed within the Compaſs of a Wafer no bigger than a Six-pence, nay within the compaſs
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:95039:17"/>of every Crumb of that Wafer, though not ſo big as a Pins-head. But I am interrupted from proceeding any further in this Attempt; for by a wonderful Conveyance, the very Subject-Matter of my Demonſtration is taken away; and inſtead of a Solid Body, with Figure and Dimenſions, with different and diſtinct parts, diviſible and meaſura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, they have left me only the Appearance of a Body, which no Demonſtration can faſten upon. For they ſay, <hi>That this Body is indued with a Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural manner of Exiſtence, by which being left without Extenſion of Parts, it may be whole in every part of the Symbols, and not obnoxious to any Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>real Contingencies.</hi> Now tho we cannot demonſtrate any Property of ſuch an incomprehenſible Body as this is, (no more than we can draw the Picture of a Non-entity, or weigh it in a Pair of Scales) for it ſcorns and tramples upon all the Principles and Axioms of <hi>Euclid;</hi> yet we may a little conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Terms of Art by which it is expreſt.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is <hi>a Body without Extenſion of Parts.</hi> So that it is a whole which has Parts, though thoſe Parts are without Extenſion; and accordingly as it follows, <hi>It may be whole in every Part of the Symbols.</hi> But if the Parts be without Extenſion, ſo is the Whole, for the Whole is nothing elſe but all the Parts put together. Now at this rate, a Part is as big as the Whole, and has as much Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſion, becauſe either of them has none at all. Is this indeed the Body which the Wonder-working Prieſt produces! A Body without Extenſion is a mere Nothing, and a perfect Contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:95039:18"/>in Terms; for Extenſion is the very Eſſence of a Body, and the Foundation of all the other Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties that are in it; the 3 Dimenſions, as alſo Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure, Diviſibility, and Impenetrability, do all flow from it. Again; ſo much as you add to the Quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of a Body, ſo much you add to the Subſtance; and ſo much of the Extenſion as you take away, juſt ſo much of the Subſtance goes along with it. In a word, Body and Extenſion are Reciprocal, for every Body is an extended Subſtance, and every extended Subſtance is a Body; ſo that they are but different Names for the ſame thing.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This Body is <hi>whole in every part of the Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bols,</hi> that is, of the Elements of Bread and Wine. But the Bread has, ſuppoſe, an Hundred diſtinct Parts, one of which is not the other, and therefore this Body being Whole in every diſtinct Part, has an Hundred diſtinct Wholes, one of which is not the other, and yet is but One Body all the while, which, as I take it, is Contradiction by whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſale.</p>
            <p n="3">3. This Body <hi>is not Obnoxious to any Corporeal Contingencies.</hi> If it be a Body, what may happen to one Body, may happen to another. To uſe <hi>Terence</hi>'s words in this caſe, <hi>Homo ſum nihil Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manum a me alienum puto:</hi> I am a Man, and what is incident to a Man, is incident to me. And ſo if a Body could ſpeak, it would ſay, <hi>Corpus ſum nihil corporeum a me alienum puto;</hi> I am a Body, and what belongs to a Body, belongs to me. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Body is ſubject to be eaten, is ſubject to be
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:95039:18"/>preſſed and grinded with the Teeth, to be ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed down, and afterwards voided; and I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe this laſt Clauſe was added on purpoſe to avoid ſuch Inconveniencies, and to ſave the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of this Body, which they call <hi>God's Body:</hi> But in my Opinion it was a needleſs Clauſe, for a Body without Extenſion can never take hurt, nor come to any damage at all. For a man may bite till his Jaws ake, and grind all his Teeth out of his Head, before he can faſten upon that whichis not, and which never yet had any Exiſtence in the world, ſave in a parcel of inſignificant words ill put together on purpoſe to amuſe unwary people.</p>
            <p>It is an endleſs thing to encounter ſhadows, and to oppoſe theſe manifeſt Impoſſibilities, which are ſo contrary to the Reaſon of Mankind, that the <hi>Papiſts</hi> themſelves own they would not hold them, were it not for the ſake of <hi>Revelation:</hi> which is to be believed, they ſay, before Reaſon, and ought to outweigh all other Reaſons. They are over-ruled, they ſay, in this caſe, by the expreſs words of our Saviour, who in the ſame night in which he was Betrayed, took Bread, and ſaid, <hi>Take, Eat, This is my Body, do this in Remembrance of me;</hi> And who has all Power in Heaven and Earth to make his words good. We allow theſe words to be our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour's, neither do we queſtion his Power, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, That he accompliſhed all that he intended, and did make the Bread his Body in that ſenſe in which he meant it ſhould be. So far we are agreed on both ſides. The Queſtion therefore in ſhort is
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:95039:19"/>this, What he did to the Bread, when he ſaid, <hi>This is my Body?</hi> Whether he Metamorphoſed and chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the nature of it? or only altered the uſe of it, that it might be a Token of his Body, and ſerve to remember him by, to all thoſe excellent purpoſes of Religion which we acknowledg to be deſign'd by him.</p>
            <p>This latter is undoubtedly the true ſenſe, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering all the circumſtances of the place. As (1st.) conſidering that our Saviour was upon his Depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, at which time men uſe to leave Memorials of themſelves with their Friends, to be Remembred by in their Abſence. (2ly.) Conſidering that the frequent uſe of the word <hi>Is,</hi> imports no more than <hi>Signifies.</hi> As in very many Places, where the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture ſays one thing is another, it means only that that thing muſt be Expounded by the Other, it ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies or ſtands for the other: And conſequently, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> i. e. This <hi>ſignifies</hi> my Body, is the Literal ſenſe. And (3ly,) conſidering that Clauſe which ſhews the end and meaning of this whole paſſage, and is the very Key to unlock it, <hi>Do this in Remembrance of me.</hi> For it is an abſurd ſpeech to ſay, Take my Body in Remembrance of my Body; Take me for a Token to Remember me by. So that if there were not one Contradiction or Impoſſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or any ſuch Rock to be ſhunned in the Doctrine of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> yet every thing in the Text leads us into this ſenſe, which I have now deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; We are plainly determined to this ſenſe, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons taken out of the very bowels of the Text; the Text expounds its ſelf.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:95039:19"/>
            <p>But ſtill the <hi>Papiſts</hi> are very urgent and preſſing upon us, and ſay, That unleſs we believe the Bread to be changed into Chriſt's Real and Natural Body, when he ſays it <hi>Is</hi> his Body, we make him a <hi>Lyar.</hi> Take heed of that. For our Saviour calls many things by the name of thoſe things into which they never were ſubſtantially changed. He called his Body a Temple, when he ſaid, <hi>Deſtroy this Temple, and in three days I will rear it up:</hi> And yet his Body was never ſubſtantially changed into a Pile of Building. And ſo likewiſe when that Temple was in deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and our Bleſſed Redeemer was hanging upon the Croſs, we have a marvellous tender paſſage of his dutiful care to provide for his Mother, when he was in the extremity of his ſufferings, <hi>Joh.</hi> 19.26, 27. ſeeing his Mother and his Diſciple <hi>John</hi> ſtanding together by the Croſs, he ſaid to her, <hi>Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, behold thy Son.</hi> Which was equivalent to this Propoſition, That Man is thy Son. And he ſaid to <hi>John, Behold thy Mother;</hi> wherein he calls the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin <hi>Mary John</hi>'s Mother, which ſhe was not. But upon this <hi>John</hi> took her for his Mother, <hi>and carried her home to his own Houſe.</hi> And ſo in this preſent caſe, <hi>This is my Body.</hi> Look not upon this as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Bread, for it ſtands for my Body; conſider it under that notion, and remember me by it. <hi>Behold thy Mother:</hi> Repute her as ſuch. But if it be a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection upon our Saviour to ſay that it is Bread, when he calls it his Body, is it not the ſame Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to ſay, That it is not Bread, when he calls it Bread three or four times over? 1 Cor. 11.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:95039:20"/>
            <p>No, no, it was not Scripture which led the <hi>Papiſts</hi> into the Doctrine of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation;</hi> but by en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaging themſelves in the defence of Image worſhip, they were betrayed into it; and were driven to take ſhelter and ſanctuary in it, to avoid the force of an Argument which they could not otherwiſe anſwer. Every body knows, that when Image-worſhip was firſt ſet up, there was a great number of Chriſtians who ſtoutly oppoſed it, and gathered Councils to condemn it; and theſe went by the name of <hi>Image-Breakers.</hi> On the other ſide the <hi>Image worſhippers</hi> were furiouſly bent upon it, and gathered Councils to maintain it, particularly that famous one of Bleſſed Memory, the ſecond <hi>Nicene</hi> Council. In theſe Oppoſitions and Diſputes, one Argument which the Image-breakers made uſe of in Reference to the Images of our Saviour, was this. If our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour has left one Image of himſelf, which is of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Inſtitution, then it is not lawful to erect other Images of him which are of humane invention; But he has left one Image of himſelf, (namely in the Sacrament) which is of Divine Inſtitution, <hi>Ergo.</hi> To make it good, That the Sacrament was an Image of our Saviour of his own Appointment, they ſhew that all the Ancient Fathers had called it the Image, the Figure, the Type, the Antitype, the Reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance or Repreſentation of our Saviour. This very Argument was uſed by the preceding Council at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and is recited by the <hi>Nicene</hi> Council, which was preſently after. But how does the <hi>Nicene</hi> Council anſwer it? They could not deny the Major Propoſition, and therefore they were forced to break through the Minor after this faſhion: They ſay
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:95039:20"/>that the Sacrament is not the Image, Reſemblance, Figure, Type, Antitype of our Saviour, but his own Body; for he himſelf expreſly ſays, <hi>Hoc eſt corpus meum.</hi> It is not therefore an Image or Figure of him, but it is he himſelf in Perſon. And thus they reſcued and diſengaged themſelves from a very cloſe and diſtreſſing Argument, and ſo their ſhow of Image<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worſhip went on.</p>
            <p>This is the firſt time that the <hi>Literal</hi> Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, as they call it, of <hi>Hoc est corpus meum,</hi> is to be met with, which it is plain likewiſe the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Council was not aware of; for if they could have foreſeen ſo full and ſo ready an Anſwer, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſenſe would never have ſuffered them to make uſe of that Argument. Now after the Literal In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation was thus broached to ſerve a preſent turn, and they had uſed it as a man does the next thing that comes to hand to ſtop a gap, it was yet a long time before <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed as a Doctrine of Faith: It had done good ſervice in ſolving an Argument, and the Image-Breakers were all broken and deſtroyed themſelves, and therefore there was no further occaſion for it. But in proceſs of time they could not but diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver many other advantages in it; as, amongſt the reſt, That it would deck the Prieſthood with the higheſt honour in the world, and advance them above all Thrones and Crowned Heads, if it were once believed that they could <hi>make</hi> their <hi>Maker</hi> when they pleaſed. And therefore it is no wonder that they were ſo very ſharp upon <hi>Berengarius,</hi> when he ſet himſelf to oppoſe it. And from that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:95039:21"/>time forwards they were forming this Doctrine into ſhape, and at laſt, four hundred and odd years after the firſt invention of it, it was made an Article of Faith in the Great <hi>Lateran</hi> Council, and Chriſtened by the name of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation.</hi> This was done by a good Token in King <hi>John</hi>'s time, when the Pope made himſelf Landlord of the Realm of <hi>England,</hi> and put it under a ſervile Tribute, which laſted for ſeveral Kings Reigns. Thus you ſee the Riſe of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> which came not into the world by the <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſticking cloſe to the Scripture, but by their cleaving to the Idolatry of Image-worſhip; whereby they are <hi>faln,</hi> according to <hi>David</hi>'s imprecation, <hi>from one wickedneſs to another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what we call an Idol, that they ſay is God's Body, which they affirm to be the plain and <hi>literal</hi> ſenſe of thoſe words, <hi>This is my Body;</hi> let us therefore ſee at laſt what their <hi>Literal</hi> Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition is. Now it runs after this manner. This which I now give you to eat was lately Bread, but I have changed the ſubſtance of the Bread into the ſelf-ſame Body with which I now deliver it to you: I tell you the late Bread is I my ſelf, it is mine own Body.
<note n="*" place="margin">Catech. Trid. de Euch. <hi>Sect.</hi> 31.</note> For in that which you now have in your hands, aſſure your ſelves there is whole Chriſt; I am there Body and Soul, yea, and my Divinity is there alſo: So that there is contained under the appearance of that bit of Bread, my Divine Nature, and my whole Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature which conſiſts of my Soul, and all the parts of my Body, together with my Blood.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:95039:21"/>My true real Natural Body which was born of the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> is there, together with whatſoever belongs to a true Humane Body, as Bones and Sinews, You will ſay that notwithſtanding all that I have ſaid, it appears to be Bread ſtill. That is true; for though the ſubſtance of the Bread be gone, yet the figure, colour, ſmell, taſte, and all the other Qualities and Conditions of the Bread remain, and
<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 44. Ipſa ſe, nulla alia re niſa ſubſtentant.</note> hang by Geometry.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 46. Nam cum a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muni Homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num naturâ maximè ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horreat Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manae carnis eſca, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> And this I have moſt wiſely ordered: For theſe Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents of Bread diſguiſe my Body, That it may the better go down, and that you may not be filled with horror at the eating of Man's fleſh, which humane nature deteſts. And then beſides, what would the Infidel world ſay, if they ſaw you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring your Lord, and eating him up in his own ſhape? And laſtly, this way of Receiving of my Body, the more remote it is from your ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, the better it is for the improvement of your Faith, and will make it the more Meritorious. But you will wonder, eſpecially now I am by in Perſon, and you have an opportunity of compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring this one ſame Body together, how this large Body which you ſee is at leaſt five Foot and a half long, and of a proportionable bulk, can be contained at the ſame time within the compaſs of a ſmall crumb of Bread, without any Alteration at all; for it is the ſelf ſame body within the Sacrament, as it is without. Now you may ſoon be ſatisfied in that Point.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 43<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> For as I am now ſitting at Table, I am in the condition of other bodies which are in a place, which are always endued with Magnitude; but the other ſame I
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:95039:22"/>which am in the Sacrament, am not as in a place, but I am there as a ſubſtance, and under that notion I am neither big nor little, for that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to Quantity, which is in another Predica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. For the ſubſtance of the Bread is turned into my ſubſtance, not into my Magnitude or Quantity. Now no body doubts but a ſubſtance may be contained in a little room as well as in a great. For both the ſubſtance of Air, and its whole Nature, muſt be alike in a ſmall portion of Air as in a greater, as alſo the whole nature of Water no leſs in a ſmall Pitcher, than in a River. Seeing therefore that my Body ſucceeds and comes in the place of the ſubſtance of the bread, you muſt acknowledg, That my Body is in the Sacrament plainly after the ſame manner, as the ſubſtance of the bread was before the Conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But to ſay, whether the ſubſtance of the bread was under a greater bulk, or under a leſs, was nothing at all to the thing.</p>
            <p>Now this Expoſition of theſe words, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> is an Authentick and Infallible Expoſition, for it is the very Interpretation of them which the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church delivers to all her Pariſh Prieſts in the <hi>Trent</hi>-Catechiſm, which was written on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe for their inſtruction; ſo that I have taken it from the Fountain head, and have it at the firſt hand. This they ſay is the meaning of thoſe words of our Saviour, <hi>This is my Body;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they make our Saviour to ſay all this: which is ſuch a ſenſe of his words, as any conſiderate Chriſtian would ſooner die, than put it upon them.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:95039:22"/>
            <p>Is this the <hi>Literal</hi> Senſe, and proper Meaning of an Organized Human Body, That it has no Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitude, and is neither Little nor Big? That it is a Solid, Maſſy Bulk, conſiſting of Fleſh and Blood, Bones and Sinews, and yet can be perceived by no Senſe; can neither be ſeen, felt, nor under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, but only Believed? That it has a Head, Trunk, and Four large Limbs, which may all be contained in the compaſs of a Pins-head; which, according to the <hi>Letter,</hi> will not hold the Fourth part of a Little-finger Nail? Methinks theſe are all ſtrange <hi>Figures,</hi> and the moſt harſh Abuſes of Speech imaginable. At this rate, the <hi>Literal</hi> Senſe of <hi>Eaſt,</hi> is <hi>West,</hi> and the <hi>Literal</hi> Senſe of Noon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day is Midnight. The <hi>Private Spirit</hi> never made ſuch Expoſitions as theſe, neither would any man alive receive them, if he were not firſt Practis'd upon, and his Belief widened for that Purpoſe. We have an Inſtance of theſe Preparatory Arts in the 42d Section, where the Paſtors are charged if they cannot otherwiſe avoid diſcourſing of theſe Matters, <hi>To remember in the first place that they fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arm the minds of the Faithful, with that ſaying,</hi> Luke 1.37. <hi>For with God nothing ſhall be Impoſſible.</hi> This is neither better nor worſe than one of their Pious Frauds; for I am ſure they know, that this Scripture is very deceitfully applied to the Caſe of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation.</hi> The Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> ſcrupled the Poſſibility of her being a Mother when ſhe knew not a Man, and asked, <hi>How this thing could be?</hi> Upon this the Angel told her, That the <hi>moſt High</hi> would employ his Power in it, and bring it to paſs in an extraordinary way, to whom nothing was
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:95039:23"/>Impoſſible: And the Omnipotence of God was a juſt ground of her Belief upon this occaſion, who very well knew, That as God had made the Firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> ſo if he pleaſed he could make the Second, without the Concurrence of either Man or Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man; and as he had formed <hi>Eve</hi> of her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band's Rib, ſo he could make the Meſſiah of the Subſtance of his Mother. So that tho this was beſide the common Courſe of Nature, yet God was not tyed to that; for what he had done, he might do again. But what Argument is this to induce the belief of Tranſubſtantiation, which involves ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold Contradictions, which the Papiſts them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves acknowledg do not fall under the Divine Power? They themſelves know full well that the Scripture ſays, <hi>It is Impoſſible for God to Lye,</hi> to whom nothing is Impoſſible; and he who can do all things, <hi>cannot deny himſelf,</hi> becauſe theſe are Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions to his own Being. And for the like reaſon they know that he cannot make a Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction in any kind, becauſe a Contradiction de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroys it ſelf, it has within it ſelf an utter Repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance to Being. To make a Thing to be, and not to be, at the ſame time, is ſuch an Inconſiſtency, that one part of it overthrows the other; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is no Act of Poſſibillty, but is an utter Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibility, which is the Contradiction of all Power, even of that which is Infinite. Methinks St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi> very well lays open the Reaſon, why an Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty Power cannot make a Contradiction. <hi>Contra Fauſtum</hi> l. 26. c. 5. <hi>Quiſquis dicit, ſi Omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens eſt Deus, faciat ut quae facta ſunt facta non fuerint, non videt hoc ſe dicere, ſi Omnipotens eſt, faciat ut ea
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:95039:23"/>quae vera ſunt, eo ipſo quo vera ſunt, falſa ſint.</hi> Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſays, If God be Almighty, let him make thoſe things which have been Done, never to have been Done, does not ſee that he ſays this in other words, If he be Almighty, let him make the things which are True, to be Falſe, even wherein they are True. So that the Angel does not tell us in this Text, That the Doctrine of Tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>ſhall not be Impoſſible with God;</hi> he does not tell us that God can make a Heap of Contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions: No, for if all the Angels of Heaven (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to St. <hi>Auſtin</hi>'s Expreſſion) ſhould ſay, <hi>That a Thing may be Falſe, even wherein it is True;</hi> ſo may what they ſay be, and conſequently there is no believing of them, nor indeed of any Being in the World upon thoſe Terms. We are able there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to bring their Expoſitions of Scripture upon this occaſion, to this Infallible Teſt. If they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contain in them things Contradictious and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, then they are not the True Senſe and Meaning of that Revelation which came from God, for if he cannot Do an Impoſſibility, neither can he Say it.</p>
            <p>And juſt ſuch as their Divinity Expoſitions are, ſo deceitful are their Philoſophical Illuſtrations: As particularly, when they ſhew, how the whole Body of Chriſt may be in the leaſt Particle, or Crumbling of the Bread, by the Two Inſtances of Air and Water. Their words are theſe,
<note place="margin">Sect. 43.</note> 
               <q>The Subſtance of Bread is turned into the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Chriſt, not into his Magnitude or Quantity. Now no body doubts but a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:95039:24"/>may be contained in a little room as well as in a great. For both the Subſtance of Air, and its whole Nature, muſt be alike in a ſmall portion of Air, as in a greater; as alſo the whole Nature of Water, no leſs in a ſmall Pitcher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, than in a River.</q> In theſe words there are no leſs than two Egregious Fallacies. For, 1. Their Inſtances are of Homogeneous or Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milar Bodies, that is, ſuch Bodies whoſe Parts are all Alike, and which have the ſame Name and Nature; ſo every Part of Air is Air, and every drop of Water is Water, and has the whole Nature of Water in it, as well as that Aggregate body of it, which is in the Ocean: But theſe Inſtances are very deceitfully applied to an Heterogeneous Diſſimilar Organized Body, as a Human Body is, which conſiſts of Parts altogether Unlike, and of Different Names and Natures. For Bone is not Fleſh, nor either of them Blood, nor any of them Brain. The Thumb nail has not the whole Nature of the Eye, nor the Skull of the Cawl: The Hand is not the Heart, nor the Head the Foot. And as theſe Parts are of Different Natures, ſo there is a Neceſſity of their keeping a conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Diſtance in their Situation, becauſe there are many Eſſential Parts of the body interpoſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt them, which would otherwiſe be ſwallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up.</p>
            <p>But 2ly, Suppoſe an Human Body were no Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound, but as pure Element as Air or Water, yet the ſame Subſtance could not be contained in a leſs room as well as in a greater. For the Air which
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:95039:24"/>is contained in a Bubble, is indeed a Subſtance of Air, but it is not the ſame Subſtance of Air as fills a Chamber, for it is not the Hundredth part of that Subſtance. Nor is a Spoonful of Water the ſame Subſtance with an Hogſhead of Water; for an Hogſhead of Water cannot be contained in a Spoon, but is at leaſt a Thouſand Spoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuls: And in common Arithmetick, Units are not the ſame with Thouſands. So that when they bring Air and Water to prove that the ſame Subſtance may be contained in a little room, as well as in a greater, their Proofs ſeem to partake of the Nature of thoſe Two Elements, for they are as Light as the one, and as Weak as the other.</p>
            <p>This tedious Digreſſion, which has proceeded to an unexpected length, has not been wholly Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable; for I have again recovered Materials out of the Infallible Expoſition it ſelf, to furniſh my intended Demonſtration, which I ſhall now re-aſſume. In the 31ſt Section we are told, That the Real Body of Chriſt is in the Sacrament, and whatſoever belongs to the Nature of a Body, as Bones and Sinews: And that All the Parts of the Body are contained in it; and in the ſmalleſt Crumb of it, <hi>Sect.</hi> 42. From whence I gather, That if All the Parts of the Body are contained in the ſmalleſt Crumb, then the Hand is, which is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of the Parts of the Body; and if the whole Hand, then all the Fingers and Thumb, for they are Parts of the Hand, which is Part of the Body; and for the ſame reaſon if all the fingers, then all the joynts of thoſe fingers. Now I want but One
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:95039:25"/>joynt of any one Finger to manifeſt the Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions and Abſurdities of this Doctrine; nay, the Bone in the firſt joynt of the fore-finger will ſerve the Turn. Now a Bone is a ſolid firm hard Subſtance, which as to its Uſe ſerves to ſtrengthen the fabrick of the Body. And if it have not theſe Properties, it is not a Bone, it is not the thing we ſpeak of; for a fluid looſe or ſoft Subſtance is not a Bone, neither will it ſerve for the above mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Uſe in the Body. Having therefore theſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties, it conſiſts of Parts Extended Impenetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and firmly joined together, ſo that they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſeparated without great force, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently they reſiſt the Touch, and feel Hard. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, this Bone in particular is of a Cylindrical Figure, an Inch long, and as much in compaſs round about. Now if any of the Parts of this Bone be Diminiſhed, then All the Parts of the Body are not there, for the Parts of this Bone which are Parts of the Body, are not there: And if the Parts be Altered, the Nature of the Thing is deſtroyed, and it is not a Bone.</p>
            <p>So that with much ado we have gained a Bone Entire, of an Inch in Magnitude, which according to the Infallible Doctrine is contained in a Crumb of the Sacrament of the Compaſs of a Pins-head. Now the Fortieth Part of this Bone is equal to that Crumb, as is manifeſt either by applying them to one another, or by their filling the ſame Place; but the Crumb is Greater than the whole Bone, for it Contains it, and therefore the Fortieth Part of the Bone is Greater than the whole Bone,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:95039:25"/>which is Impoſſible. So that the whole Bone cannot Poſſibly be Contained in that Crumb, but yet it is Contained in it, which is a plain Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction. <hi>Q. E. D.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Corollary.</hi> Now if that Bone cannot be Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in ſuch a Crumb of the Sacrament, much leſs can the whole Body, for that Bone is not the Five hundredth Part of the Whole Body: Which we have proved, by the Hypotheſis, to be there Full and Entire, and in its Juſt Dimenſions; becauſe <hi>All the Parts of the Body are there,</hi> and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently Every Part of Every Member of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, which make up the Integrity of the whole. So that we have here at Once about Twenty Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Contradictions, that is to ſay, ſo many Impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibilities.</p>
            <p>Again, This is an Everlaſting Truth, <hi>Thoſe things which are Equal to One and the ſame thing, are Equal to one another:</hi> Inſomuch that all the Syllogiſms and Demonſtrations in the World are in a manner built upon this Axiome: And who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever gainſays it, muſt aſſert one of theſe Two Things, Either that One and the Same thing is not the Same; Or elſe that what is Equal, is not Equal at the ſame time. Now a Body of Five Foot and an half long, and One Foot Diameter, is equal to the Natural Body of Chriſt; but a Crumb of Bread leſs than a Pins-head is equal to the ſelf-ſame Natural Body of Chriſt, for a Crumb of Bread as big as a Pins-head is bigger than the Natural Body of Chriſt, and Contains it, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:95039:26"/>a Crumb of Bread leſs than a Pins-head, is equal to a Body of Five Foot and an half long, and One Foot Diameter.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, by another Undeniable Maxim, which ſays, <hi>If of Equal things you take as much from the One as from the Other, the Remainders ſhall be Equal,</hi> Let us take the Quantity of a Pins-head from the Body of Five Foot and an half long, and there remains a Body of Five Foot, Five Inches, and Two Barley Corns, and ſomewhat better: Let us likewiſe take the ſame Quantity of a Pins-head from the Crumb of Bread which is leſs than a Pins-head, and there remains <hi>Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation,</hi> that is to ſay, ſomething Worſe and Leſs than Nothing. Nevertheleſs, becauſe they are the Equal Remainders of Equal Bodies, as much having been taken away from the one as from the other, I ſay that the Remainder of the Crumb is Equal to the Remainder of the Body of Five Foot and an half long, which is clearly Impoſſible. <hi>Q. E. D.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this laſt Demonſtration, for diſpatch ſake, I have been forced to do as the Papiſts do, and to lay Contradictions and Impoſſibilities upon Heaps, becauſe I haſten to proceed to other Heads: Only I muſt ſtay to Demonſtrate ſome Groſs Contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, which may be referred either to this Head of Quantity, or to the former of Place.</p>
            <p>Suppoſing Chriſt's Natural Body to be five Foot and an half long, and one Foot Diameter,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:95039:26"/>if the ſelf-ſame body be in another place at the ſame time, where ever it is, the ſelf-ſame body muſt have the ſelf-ſame Dimenſions, as we have already proved; and conſequently if it be in four ſeveral places at once,
<note place="margin">Coroll. 1.</note> it is but five Foot and an half long, and at the ſame time it is four times five Foot and an half long, which is two and twenty Foot long: And ſo likewiſe it is but one Foot Diameter, and at the ſame time it is four times one Foot Diameter, which is two Foot Diameter. And by the vaſt number of Places in which the <hi>Papiſts</hi> have beſtowed it, it will be but five Foot and an half long, and one Foot Diameter, and at the ſame time it will be as big as Mount <hi>Atlas,</hi> or <hi>Pen Men Maur,</hi> or the <hi>Pic</hi> of <hi>Tenariff.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. The fourth Head of Contradictions are thoſe which relate to <hi>Number,</hi> in ſpight of which the <hi>Papiſts</hi> make ten thouſand ſeveral bodies to be but one and the ſame body. Now as we have already proved it to be impoſſible for one and the ſame body to be in ſeveral diſtant Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſo we ſhall here demonſtrate that it is equally impoſſible for what is in ſeveral diſtant Places to be one and the ſame body.</p>
            <p>The Unity of a body conſiſts in this, <hi>That it be undivided from it ſelf, and divided from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> other Bodies;</hi> ſo that if a body be an Individual body, that is to ſay one and the ſame, it muſt be undivided from it ſelf, Now if Chriſt's body in the <hi>Pix</hi> at <hi>Limeſtreet</hi> be the ſame Individual
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:95039:27"/>body which is in the <hi>Pix</hi> at St. <hi>James</hi>'s, or at <hi>Poſnanie</hi> in the Higher <hi>Poland,</hi> then the ſelf-ſame Individual body is both undivided from it ſelf, and divided from it ſelf. For in the former caſe the ſame Individual body is divided from it ſelf not only by two
<note n="*" place="margin">Trent. Cat. de Euch. Sect. 30. Admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bili Integu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento.</note> 
               <hi>Wonderful Coverlets</hi> of the Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents of bread, and by the leſs wonderful Covers of two <hi>Pixes,</hi> but alſo by the greateſt part of two great Cities <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi> And in the latter caſe of <hi>Poſnanie</hi> in <hi>Poland,</hi> it is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided from it ſelf by vaſt Tracts of Land, and a very wide Sea; ſo that the ſelf-ſame individual body is undivided from it ſelf, and yet at the ſame time is divided from it ſelf, which is impoſſible. <hi>Q. E. D.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the other hand, There is not any thing which more Infallibly proves a real diſtinction betwixt Subſtances, and ſhews that they are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, and that the one is not the other, than this, <hi>That the one can be without the other, and that they can exiſt ſeparately and apart.</hi> Now Chriſt's body at <hi>Limeſtreet</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> and Chriſt's body at <hi>Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanie</hi> in <hi>Poland</hi> do exiſt ſeparately and apart, for it is a long and weary Pilgrimage to go from one to the other: And the one can be without the other, for that body at <hi>Poſnanie</hi> was many years without the other, and had raiſed thirty ſix Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons from the Dead long before the body at <hi>Lime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreet</hi> was made. And therefore theſe are diſtinct and divers Bodies, that is to ſay, they are not the ſame Body; And yet they are the ſame Body, which is impoſſible. Which was to be Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:95039:27"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Corollary.</hi> It is to be ſuppoſed that when Anti-Chriſt comes with Lying Wonders, no body will be ſo Unmannerly as to call them Lying Wonders, and therefore we ſhall not Queſtion the Truth of any one of thoſe Miracles which are in the <hi>School of the Euchariſt</hi>
               <note n="(2)" place="margin">Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh,</hi> and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at <hi>London</hi> 1687.</note>: Only thus much we gather from the Former Demonſtration, That the good Example of the Birds,
<note n="(b)" place="margin">School of the Euchariſt, <hi>pag.</hi> 2, 4, 7, 8, 19, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> Beaſts and Vermin, which worſhipped Gods Body in other Ages and Countries, is wholly Uſeleſs to us. For the Gods Body which is at <hi>Limeſtreet,</hi> and St. <hi>James</hi>'s, or any where here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts to be had, is not the ſame Gods Body which thoſe Devout Creatures meekly Worſhipped, and which the Stubborn Black Horſe
<note n="(c)" place="margin">Preface to the School of the Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt, <hi>pag.</hi> 22.</note> was forced to Worſhip with one Knee; and therefore we are not in a capacity of Worſhipping the ſame Gods Body, if we would.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The next Head of Contradictions is of thoſe that ariſe from the conſideration of that ſpace or <hi>Diſtance</hi> which is betwixt one body and another, which is always meaſured by a ſtraight Line drawn from a point of the one body, to a point of the other body; which is the ſhorteſt Line that can be drawn betwixt them, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly there can be but one ſtraight line drawn be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the ſame Terms, which meaſures and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes the juſt diſtance of them. Now we are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to draw a ſtraight Line from any one Point to another.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>
               <hi>Corollary.</hi> From the ſame Demonſtration it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows that St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s in <hi>Rome, Corpus Christi</hi> Church at <hi>Poſnanie</hi> in <hi>Poland,</hi> and other the remoteſt pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:95039:28"/>in the world where God's Body is, are as near Neighbours to the <hi>Monument</hi> in <hi>Fiſhſtreet</hi> as the very Maſs-houſe in <hi>Limeſtreet</hi> is. And there is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe an infinite variety of other Contradictions, which would reſult from drawing but half a ſcore right Lines from God's Body which is in ſo many ſeveral Quarters, which ſhould all meet together in the Point C. which, as the meaneſt Mathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tician eaſily underſtands, would not only confound all Diſtances, but alſo overthrow all the Everlaſting Principles of Geometry.</p>
            <p n="6">6. The Sixth Head of Contradictions is in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to Quality, whereby a Thing is rendred Like or Unlike to another. Now the ſelf-ſame Body of Chriſt, by the Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation has quite contrary Qualities, and is Like and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like to it ſelf at the ſame time. For in Heaven it is in Form of an Human Body, and in Earth it is in Form of Bread. And ſo again upon Earth, it has a Light about it like a Pillar of Fire which reaches up to Heaven, and it has not ſuch a Light about it at the ſame time. It is ſtabbed by a Jew, and is Red with Blood, and at the ſame time the ſame Body has no Redneſs nor Mark of Blood upon it. It is marked with a Crucifix, and at the ſame time it is not marked with a Crucifix, but with I H S and a Glory. Now theſe are mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt Contradictions, for the ſelf-ſame thing is af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed and denied of the ſelf-ſame Body at the ſelf-ſame time.</p>
            <p>But before I proceed to Demonſtrate the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:95039:29"/>and Impoſſibilities which fall under this Head, leſt I ſhould loſe all my pains in ſo doing, it will be fit to conſider a ſhuffling Anſwer which the Papiſts have invented to rid their hands of all Contradictions of this kind. It is in theſe words, <hi>A Body in two Places is Equivalent to Two Bodies, and therefore one may ſay of it the moſt Oppoſite things without Contradiction.</hi> It ſeems this is no new Anſwer, but I confeſs it was New to me; for I firſt met with it in the late Six Conferences con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Euchariſt, <hi>p.</hi> 89. where that very Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and Judicious Author has anſwered it, and ſent it home again with ſuch Arguments <hi>ad Hominem,</hi> as would cloſe the Mouths of any body but Papiſts. But becauſe it now alſo lies juſt croſs my way, I ought likewiſe to ſay ſomething to it.</p>
            <p>1st, Therefore I ſay, That the Suppoſition of One Body in Two Places at once, is an utter Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibility; which I have already Demonſtrated over and over again, both under the 1ſt Head of Place, and alſo under the 4th Head of Number. 2ly, One Body Equivalent to Two, that is, One Body which to all Intents and Purpoſes is Two, is a Contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in Terms; for at this rate One and One is Three, and Three and One is Five, and in ſhort, there is a full end of all Arithmetick. 3ly, It is not One Body in Two Places which will ſerve their turn, but it muſt be One Body in Ten Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Places. For it muſt be One Body in form of Fleſh, and the ſame Body in form of New Bread, and the ſame Body in form of Old Bread, and the ſame Body in form of Sweet Wine, and the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:95039:29"/>ſame Body in form of Sowre Wine, and the ſame Body at <hi>Limestreet,</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> at <hi>Avignion,</hi> and in a word, in all Places, where a bit of Bread, a Maſs Prieſt, and a Slate are to be found together. And this, as I have already ſhewn, draws after it Millions of Millions of Contradictions. 4thly, I ſay, That even the Impoſſible Suppoſition of One Body in ſeveral Places, does plainly deny all Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and Diſſimilitude in that Body; it allows indeed a Multiplication of the ſame Body, but it perfectly excludes any Alteration of it: For if it be Altered, it is not the Body which was ſuppoſed to be Multiplied. For inſtance, I will ſuppoſe the ſame Pint of Milk to be in ſeveral Places, but then it muſt be a Pint of Milk in all thoſe Places. For I cannot ſay, without Contradiction, That the ſame Pint of Milk in another Place is neither Pint, Half pint, nor Spoonful, but perhaps an unper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivable Drop, for then it is a Pint and not a Pint. And ſo likewiſe I cannot ſay, That it is a Pint of Milk in this Place in the form of Milk, and in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Place it is a Pint of Milk in form of <hi>Aqua vitae,</hi> having the Smell, Taſte, Colour and Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues of <hi>Aqua vitae:</hi> In another Place it is a Pint of Milk in the form of a Pen-full of Ink: And in another Place it is a Pint of Milk in the form of a Bandelier full of Gunpowder. For in theſe caſes it is ſo Altered that it is not Milk, it is not the Thing we ſpoke of, and which we ſuppoſed to be Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied: And at the ſame time though it be neither Milk nor Meaſure, yet in the way of Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation it is ſtill a very good Pint of Milk. Theſe Men had bettet let their Contradictions
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:95039:30"/>alone, than offer to aſſoil them, for the Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation is perfectly of the nature of Birdlime, the more they ſtir and flutter in it, the faſter they are caught.</p>
            <p>So that this ſorry Evaſion being of the ſame piece with Tranſubſtantiation it ſelf, or rather an aggravation of Contradiction, I ſhall ſet it aſide as if it had never been, and proceed to my intended Demonſtration.</p>
            <p>We have not in our Minds a clearer and brighter firſt Principle than this is, <hi>That nothing can be Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and Abſent from the ſame Subject at the ſame time.</hi> Now the Mark of I H S is Preſent to Chriſts Body being imprinted upon it, and at the ſame time it is Abſent from the ſelf-ſame Body, having inſtead of I H S a Crucifix upon it, and therefore the Mark of I H S is Preſent to Chriſts Body, and Abſent from the ſelf-ſame Body at the ſame time, which is Impoſſible. <hi>Q. E. D.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, Gods Body in Form of Bread is not Gods Body in Form of Wine; for if it were, then the Form of Bread, and the Form of Wine would be the ſame; Wine would be Bread, and Bread would be Wine, that is to ſay, Bread would be Not Bread. But according to the Papiſts, Gods Body in Form of Bread, is Gods Body in Form of Wine, that is to ſay, Bread is not Bread, which is Impoſſible. Which was to be Demonſtrated.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:95039:30"/>
            <p n="7">7. The laſt Head of Contradictions ariſe from this part of the Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation, which ſays, <q>That when the Subſtances of Bread and Wine are aboliſhed, and wholly ceaſe to Be, ſtill all the Accidents of Bread and Wine are ſeen to Remain without any Subject at all. For the Subſtances of Bread and Wine are departed and gone, and theſe Accidents cannot cleave and be united to the Body and Blood of Chriſt, and therefore it remains, That in a Supernatural way they muſt ſubſiſt of themſelves.</q> This is their own Infallible Doctrine, <hi>Trid. Catech. de Euch. Sect.</hi> 25. <hi>&amp;</hi> 44. In which few words there is plenty of Contradictions.</p>
            <p>For (1ſt,) I ſhall Demonſtrate, That Accidents ſubſiſting without a Subject, are Subſtances, that is to ſay, are not Accidents. And becauſe the Papiſts themſelves are ſenſible how Abſurd and Impoſſible this Doctrine of theirs is, therefore they fly to Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle and Omnipotency, which is no Refuge nor Sanctuary for Contradictions and Impoſſibilities, as we have already ſhewn.</p>
            <p>Now the very Eſſence of an Accident is to ſubſiſt in a Subject, and the Eſſence of a Subſtance is to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt of it ſelf without a Subject; ſo that if God by his Omnipotency ſhould make an Accident to ſubſiſt of it ſelf without a Subject, he would give one and the ſame ſingle Thing Two contrary Natures: Whereby the ſame thing would be what it is, and would not be what it is; it would ſubſiſt in a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:95039:31"/>and not ſubſiſt in a Subject at the ſame time, which is Impoſſible. <hi>Q. E. D.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have been beholden to the great Philoſopher <hi>Des Cartes,</hi> a Man of their own Communion, for this Demonſtration, and have gathered it out of his Anſwer to the Fourth and Sixth Objections which were made againſt his Meditations, and out of his Notes upon the <hi>Programma,</hi> of <hi>Regius</hi> as I ſuppoſe. And it has been heretofore no ſmall diverſion to me to ſee how the Papiſts ſtood on Tiptoe, when that great Reſtorer of Natural Knowledg appeared, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting whether his New Philoſophy would favour their Old Tranſubſtantiation. But when they found that he was not a Man for Subſtantial Accidents, and ſuch kind of Contradictious Stuff, Dr. <hi>Arnault</hi> of the <hi>Sorbonne,</hi> puts it home to him in the Fourth Objections, and tells him, That according to his Philoſophy, the Doctrine of the Church concerning the Sacrament of the Altar could not remain ſafe and ſound; becauſe it is of Faith, That the Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents in the Sacrament remain without a Subject; whereas Monſieur <hi>Cartes</hi> ſeemed to hold, (for he had not as yet ſpoke out, nor expreſſed himſelf ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in that matter), That Accidents are Inſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble from a Subject, and that a Body, and the Aſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of that Body could not ſubſiſt apart, nor be made to Exiſt ſeparately by an Infinite Power. Wherefore Monſieur <hi>Arnauld</hi> prays him to take great care, leſt that while he is proving a God, and the Immortality of the Soul, he ſhould endanger that Faith by which himſelf hoped to be ſaved.</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:95039:31"/>
            <p>Here <hi>Cartes</hi> was beſet, and forced to declare him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and therefore was put upon his Invention, which was firſt to contrive a way of ſolving the Appearan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Bread and Wine which are in the Sacrament, by a New Hypotheſis of the Superficies; which he told them he ſhould more fully make out in his <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſics:</hi> And when he had thus firſt entertained them with a new Hypotheſis, then he ſhews them what Impoſſible Abſurdities Real Accidents are, and how full of Repugnancy and Contradictions; and that theſe Contradictions made men Diſſenters from the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> And then he concludes, That he hoped the Time would come, when the Divines of that Church would hiſs the Doctrine of Real Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents out of the world, as an Unreaſonable, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible, and Unſafe Doctrine to be Believed; and that his Superficies would be embraced inſtead of it, as Certain and Indubitable. Monſieur <hi>Arnault</hi> was a Man of ſenſe, and therefore I doubt not but he let fall his Ears at this Anſwer. And the <hi>Paris</hi> Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines ſent <hi>Cartes</hi> word afterwards in their ſixth Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections, <hi>Scruple</hi> the 7th, That they did not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand his Superficies, and knew not what to make of it: And that tho he put them in hope that he would make things plainer in his <hi>Phyſics,</hi> yet they were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined to Believe they ſhould never part with their old Opinion concerning Accidents, for his new one.</p>
            <p>But tho they were of this mind, yet we find a very conſiderable Perſon, <hi>Epiſt. Vol.</hi> 2. <hi>Epiſ.</hi> 3. who had better thoughts of it, and ſays, That he had happily ſhewn how the Inſeparableneſs of Accidents
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:95039:32"/>from a Subſtance, might be conſiſtent with the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the Altar; but then he deſires to know of <hi>Cartes,</hi> whether he had bethought himſelf of a way to Reconcile another part of his Philoſophy with Chriſts Body, being without Local Extenſion upon the Altar, for otherwiſe he would expoſe to great Peril the moſt ſacred thing in the world. Upon this <hi>Cartes</hi> ſtops ſhort, and does not care to give any thing more concerning the Sacrament under his hand, but offers to meet him if he pleaſes, and to tell him his Conjectures by word of mouth, <hi>ibid Epist.</hi> 4.</p>
            <p>And was not this a pleaſant way of proceeding? Which is in effect as if they had ſaid, Sir, You are a great Philoſopher of our own Church, you know we hold the Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation, and you your ſelf hope to be ſaved by it; ſee there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore what can be done for it, pray make it as rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable as you can. It is too like the Comical Story of the Woman, who after ſhe had eaten <hi>Pig</hi> in <hi>Smith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field,</hi> went to <hi>Rabbi Buiſy,</hi> and prays him to make the eating of <hi>Pig</hi> as lawful as he can. And is it not likewiſe a neat turn to quiet them with his Doctrine of the Superficies?</p>
            <p>Now the Superficies is much ſuch another <hi>Ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nale</hi> of Tranſubſtantiation, as the following Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument is a proof of Purgatory. If there be one whoſe words are recorded in Scripture, who when he died went neither to Heaven nor Hell, then there is ſuch a Middle place as Purgatory; but there is one whoſe words are recorded in Scripture, <hi>&amp;c.
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:95039:32"/>Ergo.</hi> I have ſeen a Papiſt catch at this Syllogiſm ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry greedily, and as Impatient to know who that One was, as if he would preſently have gone a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting with the Argument. But he was as blank when he was told that it was <hi>Balaam</hi>'s Aſs, as I fancy Dr. <hi>Arnault</hi> was, when he had read and conſidered the long Story of the Superficies; which, I believe, never yet drew one of thoſe back again to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> whom <hi>Cartes</hi> complains the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Real Accidents drove away.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This Propoſition, Nihili nullae poſſunt eſſe Affectiones, <hi>That Nothing cannot poſſibly have any Qualities or Affections,</hi> is a Neceſſary and Everlaſting Truth; and it is ſo clear and ſelf-evident, that all words and diſcourſe about it would but darken the Natural Light which is in it. Now a Wafer or ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Cake is an Extended, Round, White Subſtance, having all the Qualities and Affections of Bread; and when this Subſtance
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Sect. 25. ut Omnino eſſe deſinant.</note> wholly ceaſes to be, it is nothing. But if the Extenſion, Roundneſs, White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and all the Bready Qualities of it ſtill Remain, then at the ſame time there do Remain the Extenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the Roundneſs, the Whiteneſs, and the Bready Qualities or Affections of Nothing, which is Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible.</p>
            <p>And that Nothing, whoſe Extenſion, Roundneſs, Whiteneſs and Bready Qualities are ſtill Remaining, is an Extended, Round, White and Bready Nothing; which are ſo many Contradictions and Impoſſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. <hi>Q. E. D.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:95039:33"/>
            <p>I ſee that I muſt either break off Abruptly, or never have done. For I find the Dividing of the Accidents of a Wafer into 3 Parts, which is one of the Operations performed in the Maſs; and with the ſelf ſame Diviſion, the Dividing of Chriſt's Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy into 3 Wholes; and many more of their Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdities coming thick into my head; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I will here Conclude in time.</p>
            <p>All theſe Demonſtrations hitherto are Arguments to all Mankind, I have now an Argument or Two <hi>ad Hominem,</hi> or to the Papiſts themſelves.</p>
            <p>And 1ſt, By their own Infallible Doctrine of Concomitancy I ſhall Demonſtrate, That there has been never a God's Body, as they call it, upon Earth theſe 1600 Years; Provided they will allow me, Firſt, That Chriſt's Body has been in Heaven theſe 1600 Years. And 2ly, That Heaven and Earth are different and diſtant Places. I reckon that Infallibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity her ſelf, either has granted me both theſe <hi>Poſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lata</hi> already, in theſe following words, <hi>Tr. Cat. de Euch. Sect.</hi> 37. <hi>But it is plainly Impoſſible, That the Body of Chriſt ſhould be in the Sacrament, by coming out of one Place into another, for ſo it would come to paſs, that the Body of Chriſt would be Abſent from its Seat in Heaven;</hi> (Now I preſume, if it has not been Abſent from its Seat in Heaven, to come and be Preſent in the Sacrament theſe 1600 Years, it has not been Abſent upon any other Account): Or elſe I reckon that becauſe the things Demanded are very Reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, ſhe will not now ſtick at the Granting of them. Now the Rule of Concomitancy is this, <hi>Tr. Cat. de
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:95039:33"/>Euch. Sect.</hi> 33. Si enim duo aliqua inter ſe reipſa con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jungantur, Ubi unum ſit, ibi alterum etiam eſſe Neceſſe eſt. <hi>If any two things are Really joined toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, where the one is, there of Neceſſity the other must be alſo.</hi> That is to ſay, it is Impoſſible for it to be in any other Place. But no two things in the World are more Really joined together, than one and the ſame thing is with it ſelf; and if it were not ſo, no one thing could be Really joined to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. The Union of one and the ſame thing with it ſelf, is the moſt cloſe and intimate that can be, and conſequently the Concomitancy muſt be the ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt. Nay the very Reaſon, Ground, Bottom, and Foundation of the Rule of Concomitancy is this, Becauſe from Two ſingle Things Really joyned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, there reſults One Compound. The Union is the Cauſe of the Concomitancy, becauſe it is Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for the ſame thing to be Divided from it ſelf. So that if two things which are Really joined toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, muſt always of Neceſſity keep company toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, then it is utterly Impoſſible for one and the ſame thing to ſtraggle from it ſelf, but it muſt ever be its own Individual Companion.</p>
            <p>From theſe Premiſes I ſay, That Chriſt's Body having been in Heaven theſe 1600 Years, if in that Space of Time it has been upon Altars here on Earth, then it has not been at the ſame time where it has been, but it has broken the Rule of Conco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitancy, and has ſtrangely ſtragled from it ſelf; which is Impoſſible. <hi>Q. E. D.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have ſtudied with all the Application of Mind of which I am capable, to forecaſt in my thoughts
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:95039:34"/>what fault the Papiſts would find with any of the former Reaſonings, or with this laſt in particular, and cannot foreſee nor imagine any. For though we ſhould allow Chriſt's Body to be <hi>Independent of Place,</hi> or to have any other Impoſſible Prerogatives which they liſt to Invent, yet ſtill this Body muſt be ſubject to the Rule of Concomitancy, becauſe they themſelves are forced to make uſe of it to prove that the Body of Chriſt is under the Species of Wine, and that the Blood of Chriſt is under the Species of Bread; and it is the only Proof they have. Now if of Neceſſity the Body muſt be by Concomitancy where the Blood is, then by an ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent Neceſſity the Blood muſt be where the Blood is; for the Blood's being there is the cauſe of the Bodies being there likewiſe. So the Body being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Form of Bread, is the reaſon that the Blood is there alſo; but then to be ſure the Body muſt be there. From whence, as I ſhewed before, it undenia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly follows, That Chriſt's Body is only in Heaven; or elſe it is not where it is, which overthrows the very Foundation of Concomitancy.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Second Argument ſhall be drawn from their Form of Conſecration, <hi>For this is my Body,</hi> being the words of our Saviour from whence they have wreſted the Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation. Now to give them a Samplar of their own, and to ſhew them how they themſelves interpret Scripture, I ſay that it appears by the very words of Conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, That the Prieſt himſelf is alſo Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiated; for the Body is Chriſt's, and yet the Prieſt ſays it is <hi>My Body,</hi> which cannot be True, unleſs the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:95039:34"/>Prieſt and Chriſt be the ſame: And that cannot be, but by an Admirable Change and Converſion, which the Holy Catholick Church has conveniently and properly named Tranſubſtantiation. No, ſay the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts in great anger, There is no ſuch Change at all, for the Prieſt only ſtands for Chriſt, and
<note n="(a)" place="margin">Sect. 82. Perſonam ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipiunt Perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam gerens.</note> ſuſtains his Perſon; he only Repreſents him in that Action, and is in Chriſt's ſtead; ſo that we are not to look upon the Prieſt in that ſolemn Action as Friar <hi>John,</hi> but as Chriſt himſelf. And therefore the Prieſt may ſay with Truth, this is <hi>My Body,</hi> tho Literally and Properly, and in ſtrictneſs of Speech, it is <hi>Chriſt's Body,</hi> and not <hi>His.</hi> To which I again reply. Why this is the very Expoſition of theſe words of our Saviour, for which the Hereticks have all along been Burnt, namely, This Bread ſtands for my Body, and Repreſents it in this Action; it is inſtead of my Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and bears the Character of it; and you are not ſo much to conſider it as Bread, but to look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it as the Repreſentation of my Body, which is given for you. And therefore with Truth I can ſay it is my <hi>Body,</hi> though Literally, and Properly, and in ſtrictneſs of Speech, it is <hi>Bread,</hi> and not my <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now therefore let the Papiſts give or take. Either the Bread is not Tranſubſtantiated; or if it be, by virtue of the ſelf-ſame words the Prieſt is Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiated too. For every word in the Prolation with one Breath, (except the word <hi>Enim,</hi> Sect. 20.) does Operate as well as Signifie, and Does what it Says; and therefore if the word <hi>Corpus</hi> be effectual to make it a Body, then the word <hi>Meum</hi> makes it
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:95039:35"/>the Prieſts Body. The Wit of Man cannot find an Evaſion, and I doubt not but I am able to maintain this Argument againſt all the Popiſh Prieſts in the world. For all the Advantage lies clearly on the Proteſtant Side. For our Saviour viſibly took Bread, and gave it the office of Repreſenting him, and <hi>made it the Figure of his Body,</hi> as <hi>Tertullian</hi>'s word is; He erected it as a ſtanding Memorial to be uſed in <hi>Remembrance or Commemoration of him,</hi> as S <hi>Luke</hi>'s word is; <hi>To ſhew forth his Death till he come,</hi> as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks. 'Tis true, he commanded his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples to repeat the ſame Action, and to do as he had done; But where did he bid the Prieſt to Perſonate him? That he gave us the Bread by the Name of his <hi>Body,</hi> Three of the Four Goſpels witneſs, and by the Name of his <hi>Broken Body,</hi> S. <hi>Paul</hi> witneſſes; But where did he ever ſay, That He himſelf would always Sacrifice himſelf by the Prieſts Hands, and ſay, <hi>Hoc eſt Corpus meum,</hi> to the end of the world, by the Prieſts Mouth? And further, There is not one word which the Papiſts have ſaid in behalf of the Bread being Tranſubſtantiated, but holds as ſtrongly for the Prieſts being Tranſubſtantiated; which makes full as much for the Dignity and Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty of the Sacrament, for the abaſing and mortifying of our Deceivable Senſes, and for the improving and exalting our Faith, and making it Meritorious, as the other can.</p>
            <p>We have gained ſuch conſiderable Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages by the foregoing part of our Diſcourſe, that now we are able unalterably to renounce the Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation. For ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:95039:35"/>Demonſtrated the Impoſſibility of it, We have thereby Demonſtrated, that though Heaven and Earth ſhould paſs away, yet that Doctrine can never be True. We have likewiſe at the ſame time Demonſtrated the Proteſtant Expoſition of thoſe words of our Saviour, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> to be the true and neceſſary Senſe of them; for either there is a Change of the Bread into the Body of Chriſt, or there is not: But becauſe ſuch a Change is an utter Impoſſibility, as we have abundantly proved, therefore it remains, That the Proteſtant Doctrine, which aſſerts there is no ſuch Change, is Demonſtrably True. We have alſo made it as clear as the Light, That neither the <hi>Letter</hi> of a <hi>Divine Revelation,</hi> nor the pretence of an <hi>Infinite Power,</hi> nor any thing in the world can ſupport one ſingle Contradiction; becauſe if one ſingle Contradiction could ſtand, it would deſtroy the very Being of God himſelf, and deprive the world of the Adorable Object of all Religion. For ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing it <hi>Impoſſible for a Being of Neceſſary Exiſtence to Exiſt,</hi> which is but ſuppoſing a Contradiction, and we have immediately loſt the Author of all Divine Revelation; And not only ſo, but the whole Univerſe likewiſe muſt preſently ſink into Nothing, or rather indeed it could never have been at all.</p>
            <p>But more particularly we ſhall find the Benefit of the former Demonſtrations in the ſhort re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder of our preſent Diſcourſe, for they will add to what we have further to ſay againſt Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation all the force and ſtrength which De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration can give. <hi>Coſterus</hi> the Jeſuit acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, (and I ſuppoſe all Papiſts with him) that
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:95039:36"/>
               <hi>If the Bread be not changed into the Body of Christ, the worſhip of the Hoſt is groſs Idolatry;</hi> But we are paſt all <hi>Ifs</hi> and <hi>Ands,</hi> and have Demonſtrated that there can be no ſuch Change of the Bread into Chriſt's Body: And conſequently we have Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated that (ſuppoſing that Jeſuits Conceſſion juſt) the Papiſts in worſhipping of the Hoſt, are guilty of groſs Idolatry, and the Beſt Friends they have in the world cannot free them from it. So likewiſe it can be no longer a Moot-point, or a diſputable matter, whether it be Criminal to call the Hoſt their <hi>Lord God, their Maker, their Former, and their Creator;</hi> when we have Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated that it cannot be ſo, and that it is only a bit of Bread; and to affirm Bread to be a God, if it be not Blaſphemy, it wants a name in our Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage. In ſhort, That can never be a Divine Myſtery which is not in a Poſſibility of being a Divine Truth: And conſequently the <hi>Myſtery</hi> and <hi>Miraculouſneſs</hi> of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> which has been the old and dark ſtronghold of Popery, is ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly demoliſhed: And the Papiſts having loſt that ſhelter, not only all the Abſurdities of their Belief concerning it will fall upon them with their whole weight, but alſo all their abſurd Practices in refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to it, to which I ſhall now proceed.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond General Head is of <hi>Practical Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdities,</hi> by which I mean ſuch unreaſonable and unworthy Actions as are done by the Papiſts in purſuance of their Doctrine of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation.</hi> And here I can by no means charge them with ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their Maker, or eating Man's fleſh, and drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:95039:36"/>Man's blood in the Sacrament: For I have ſhewn it to be impoſſible for them to do either of theſe. But yet becauſe they intend and profeſs to do both, perhaps the guilt is no leſs than if they really did them. And the Abſurdity of their Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice in this behalf is very equally matched with the Abſurdity and Contradictiouſneſs of their Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief. For as they hold the Sacrament to be the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Body of Chriſt, and yet ſay it is in ſeveral Places at once, and is made at ſeveral times, and is in the Form of Bread, whereby it appears to be not the Natural Body of Chriſt, but a piece of Bread; wherein they ſay and unſay at once: So likewiſe they worſhip and ſerve, and pray to that which I have Demonſtrated to be a bit of Bread as if it were a God, and immediately they undo all that they have done, and treat him not at all like a God, but eat him up as if he were a bit of Bread. So alſo they ſay expreſly, That the common Nature of Mankind abhors the eating of Man's fleſh, and drinking of Man's blood, and yet they eat and drink that, of which they ſay they have greater Aſſurance that it is Man's fleſh, and Man's blood, than the Teſtimony of all their Senſes can give them.</p>
            <p>But omitting theſe things, and the great Indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity which is offered to our Bleſſed Saviour by ſuch like Practices, I ſhall take notice of their Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try in worſhipping a piece of Bread as if it were God himſelf. And this Practice is unavoidable Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry if the Doctrine of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> ſhould chance to be falſe: And if it be not falſe, then a
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:95039:37"/>thouſand Millions of Contradictions muſt be all of them true. So that if the Apoſtles rent their Clothes when the <hi>Lvcaonians</hi> ſaid that the <hi>Gods were come down in the likeneſs of Men,</hi> and were going to give them Divine Honour;
<note place="margin">Acts 14.11.</note> ſurely they would hardly ſpare their fleſh, but rend that too, if they ſhould be ſhewn more than an Hundred God-Almighties together in the <hi>Form of Bread,</hi> and ſhould ſee Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Worſhip paid to them: Eſpecially, ſince the Apoſtles Evangelized men to turn away from Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry to the Living God who made Heaven and Earth; if moreover the Papiſts ſhould plead Goſpel for their Idolatry, and ſay that they were Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lized into it: I have often thought what St. <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> would have ſaid and done in that Caſe. But what they then cried out and ſaid to the <hi>Lycaonians, Sirs, why do ye theſe things? For we are men of like Paſſions with you;</hi> methinks the Hoſt it ſelf ſays as loud every day to the Papiſts; <q>
                  <hi>Sirs, why do ye theſe things?</hi> For I am no Object of Worſhip, but like another piece of Bread. I have all the Properties, and am ſubject to all the Caſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alties of any other bit of Bread: For either I am preſently eaten and ſwallowed down as any other Bread is, or elſe if I be kept, I grow Stale and Mouldy. I am put into a Box for fear of Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chances, for if the Mouſe gets me, I am gone. Alas, I am Bread, I am no God.</q> Thus to my Apprehenſion the Hoſt it ſelf continually cries out and reaſons with them. And Oh would to God that they would conſider to as good purpoſe as the <hi>Lyca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onians</hi> did! I ſhould be content to endure great hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips to ſee that Happy Day.</p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:95039:37"/>
            <p>And now, <hi>O ye Papists,</hi> I have diſcharged my Conſcience; for it has troubled me that I had not long ſince laid theſe things plain and open before you. And if I knew how to incline you to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them, I would not think much to kneel down at your Feet. But if you will not conſider them with that evenneſs of mind which is always neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to Conviction, but rather will conſider them with that prejudice and indignation which ſhall put you upon Contradicting and Objecting, and uſing all your Subtilties and Evaſions; then I beg of you to do this throughly, and ſpare me not. For I have written this Diſcourſe only for the Honour of God, and out of love to Truth, which never loſes any thing by being Tried and Examined, but ſtill comes the Brighter out of the Fire. It is the Cauſe of God my Saviour who died for me, and I am willing to ſpend the remainder of my days in it, or lay down my life for it, even which of the two He ſhall pleaſe.</p>
            <p>And as for you, <hi>O ye Protestants,</hi> you have great reaſon to Bleſs God, that you were Born into the World ſince the Reformation; whereby you enjoy the Benefit of having God's own Book in your own Vulgar Tongue: And thereby are taught to know God and his Creatures aſunder, and have learnt to diſtinguiſh our Saviour Chriſt from his Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, and to know your Maker from a Bit of Bread. Who have the Advantage of reading God's pure Word, without either <hi>Romiſh</hi> Comments or <hi>Rhemiſh</hi> Annotations which overthrow the Text. Who are allowed to ſee with your own Eyes, That
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:95039:38"/>if Scripture ſhould be ſo forced and wreſted as the Papiſts have uſed it in this Caſe, then we muſt all be <hi>Anthropomorphites,</hi> and either Believe that God is of <hi>Human Shape,</hi> or elſe give him the <hi>Lye</hi> I know not how oft. For the Right Hand of God, and many other Bodily parts of him, are ten times oftner aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted in Scripture, than <hi>This is my Body.</hi> If the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts ſay, That the Scripture in affirming that God is a Spirit, does ſufficiently rectifie all ſuch blockiſh Miſtakes; I ſay ſo too: And withal, that our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our has done abundantly more to prevent and fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſe the no leſs blameable miſtake concerning Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation. For after he had called the Cup his <hi>Blood,</hi> he afterwards again called it <hi>the Fruit of the Vine;</hi> and after his Reſurrection it ſelf, he gave his Diſciples this Teſt to judg and diſcern his Body, and to know it by, <hi>Luke</hi> 24.39. <hi>Behold my hands and my feet, that it is I my ſelf: handle me and ſee: for a ſpirit hath not fleſh and bones, as ye ſee me have.</hi> From whence we are bound to conclude, That where we cannot ſee Hands and Feet, where we cannot ſee and feel Fleſh and Bones, where we cannot handle and ſee Chriſt's Body, there it is not he himſelf: Well may there be ſome Sign, or Token, or Memorial of his Body, but it cannot be <hi>he himſelf.</hi> I ſhall not ſtand to enquire whether this be the Criterion to know Human Bodies from thoſe Bodies which An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels heretofore aſſumed; but we are ſure that theſe are Infallible Marks to know our Saviour's Body by, and that is all our preſent Buſineſs.</p>
            <p>But as for the Noiſe they have lately made about our Saviour's ſurprizing the Diſciples, and entring
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:95039:38"/>into the room, <hi>when the Doors were ſhut,</hi> there ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was any thing more precarious than the ſenſe which the Papiſts have put upon that place, as if our Saviour had <hi>paſſed through the Doors.</hi> For there were Two Things, as appears by the Scripture, which diſturbed the Diſciples; Firſt, That a Perſon ſhould come into the Room without knocking or giving them any warning, when they had made all faſt, and kept themſelves cloſe <hi>for ſear of the Jews:</hi> And the Second was, That he entred in ſuch a manner as made them apprehend him to be a <hi>Spirit.</hi> Now how did ever Angels or Spirits enter into a Room, or St. <hi>Peter</hi> come out of Priſon under the conduct of an Angel, but by the Doors opening before them of their own accord, and ſhutting again after them? As in the caſe of all the Apoſtles, where the Officers <hi>found the Priſon ſhut with all ſafety,</hi> Acts 5.23. And I never yet heard or read of Angel or Spirit, which entred a Room through Crannies or Key<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holes, or through Inch-boards. But let that be as it will, if our Saviour had entred in any ſuch manner, it had abſolutely overthrown the Criterion which he gave them at the ſame time to judg of his Body, and to Demonſtrate that he was not a Spirit. For common ſenſe would have taught the Diſciples to reply, It is true indeed, whatever you are, Man or Spirit, that you have now a groſs Human Body, and we cannot deny it; but that, it ſeems, is only when you pleaſe, for you had not ſuch a one a while ago, when you were pleaſed to come in at the Key<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hole; whereas there was nothing at all of this, but they knew and owned him, and were glad to ſee the Lord. But to conclude, Is not this a very pertinent
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:95039:39"/>proof of Tranſubſtantiation, when the Doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation aſſerts a thing quite contrary to the <hi>Paſſing through Doors?</hi> For it aſſerts that our Saviour's Body is Preſent in a Room, not by being Tranſlated, or by Paſſing out of one Place into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but by being produced in all freſh Places, and by being <hi>Within Doors,</hi> and <hi>Without Doors,</hi> at the ſame Time.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, <hi>O my Proteſtant Countrymen,</hi> You are Happy, if you know your own Happineſs, and are not weary of it. While you have the Light, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joice in it, and walk worthy of it; and then God will continue it to you and to your Poſterity. <hi>So be it.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:95039:39"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Books lately Printed for</hi> W. Rogers.</head>
            <p>THE Doctrines and Practices of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> truly Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented; in Anſwer to a Book intituled, <hi>A Papiſt Miſrepreſented, and Repreſented,</hi> &amp;c. Quarto.</p>
            <p>An Anſwer to a Diſcourſe intituled, <hi>Papiſts proteſting againſt Proteſtant Popery;</hi> being a Vindication of <hi>Papiſts</hi> not <hi>Miſrepreſented</hi> by <hi>Proteſtants:</hi> And containing a particular Examination of Monſieur <hi>de Meaux,</hi> late Biſhop of <hi>Condom,</hi> his Expoſition of the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> in the Articles of <hi>Invocation of Saints, Worſhip of Images,</hi> occaſioned by that Diſcourſe. Quarto.</p>
            <p>An Anſwer to the <hi>Amicable Accommodation</hi> of the Differences between the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> and the <hi>Anſwerer.</hi> Quarto.</p>
            <p>A View of the whole Controverſie between the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> and the <hi>Anſwerer;</hi> with an Anſwer to the <hi>Repreſenter</hi>'s laſt <hi>Reply;</hi> in which are laid open ſome of the Methods by which <hi>Proteſtants</hi> are <hi>Miſrepreſented</hi> by <hi>Papiſts.</hi> Quarto.</p>
            <p>The Doctrine of the <hi>Trinity,</hi> and <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> compared as to <hi>Scripture, Reaſon,</hi> and <hi>Tradition;</hi> in a new Dialogue between a <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant</hi> and a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> the <hi>Firſt</hi> Part: Wherein an Anſwer is given to the late Proofs of the Antiquity of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> in the Books called, <hi>Conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Veterum,</hi> and <hi>Nubes Teſtium,</hi> &amp;c. Quarto.</p>
            <p>The Doctrine of the <hi>Trinity</hi> and <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> compared as to <hi>Scripture, Reaſon,</hi> and <hi>Tradition;</hi> in a new Dialogue between a <hi>Proteſtant</hi> and a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> the Second Part: Wherein the Doctrine of the <hi>Trinity</hi> is ſhewed to be agreeable to <hi>Scripture</hi> and <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> repugnant to both. Quarto.</p>
            <p>An Anſwer to the <hi>Eighth Chapter</hi> of the <hi>Repreſenter</hi>'s Second Part, in the firſt Dialogue between him and his Lay-Friend.</p>
            <p>Of the Authority of <hi>Councils,</hi> and the Rule of <hi>Faith.</hi> By a Perſon of Quality; With an Anſwer to the Eight <hi>Theſes,</hi> laid down for the Tryal of the <hi>Engliſh Reformation,</hi> in a Book that came lately from <hi>Oxford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sermons and Diſcourſes, ſome of which never before Printed; The Third Volume. By the Reverend Dr. <hi>Tillotſon,</hi> Dean of <hi>Canterbury. 8vo.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:95039:40"/>
            <p>A Manual for a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Soldier, Written by <hi>Eraſmus,</hi> and Tranſlated into <hi>Engliſh.</hi> Twelves.</p>
            <p>A new and eaſie Method to learn to <hi>Sing</hi> by Book, whereby one (who hath a good Voice and Ear) may without other help, learn to <hi>Sing</hi> true by Notes. Deſign'd chiefly for, and applied to the promoting of <hi>Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mody;</hi> and furniſhed with Variety of <hi>Pſalm-Tunes</hi> in Parts, with Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions for that kind of <hi>Singing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Book of Cyphers or Letters Reverſt; being a Work very pleaſant and uſeful, as well for Gentlemen as all ſorts of Artificers, Engravers, Painters, Carvers, Chacers, Embroiderers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Where you may find a Cypher for any Name whatſoever, curiouſly compoſed after the neweſt Mode. By <hi>Jeremiah Marlow.</hi> Price Bound 5 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Perſwaſive to frequent Communion in the <hi>Sacrament</hi> of the <hi>Lord's Supper.</hi> By <hi>John Tillotſon,</hi> Dean of <hi>Canterbury.</hi> In Octavo. Price 3 <hi>d</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Diſcourſe againſt <hi>Tranſubſtantiation.</hi> In Octavo, Price 3 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The State of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> when the Reformation began, as it appears by the Advices given to <hi>Paul</hi> III. and <hi>Julius</hi> III. by Creatures of their Own. With a Preface leading to the matter of the Book. 40.</p>
            <p>A Letter to a Friend, Reflecting on ſome Paſſages in a Letter to the D. of P. in Anſwer to the Arguing Part of his firſt Letter to Mr. G.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Reflecter's</hi> Defence of his Letter to a Friend, againſt the Furious Aſſaults of Mr. <hi>I S.</hi> in his ſecond Catholic Letter. In four Dialogues. 40.</p>
            <p>A Sermon Preached at the Funeral of the Reverend <hi>Benj. Calamy,</hi> D.D. and late Miniſter of St. <hi>Lawrence Jury, Lond. Jan.</hi> 7th, 1686. By <hi>W. Sher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock,</hi> D. D. Maſter of the <hi>Temple.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Vindication of ſome Proteſtant Principles of Church-Unity and Catholick-Communion, from the Charge of Agreement with the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> In Anſwer to a late Pamphlet, Intituled, <hi>An Agreement be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Church of</hi> England <hi>and the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>evinced from the Concertation of ſome of her Sons with their Brethren the Diſſenters.</hi> By <hi>William Sherlock,</hi> D. D. Maſter of the <hi>Temple.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Diſcourſe concerning the Nature of Idolatry; in which a late Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor's true and only Notion of Idolatry is Conſidered and Confuted. 40.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Proteſtant Reſolv'd; or, a Diſcourſe ſhewing the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreaſonableneſs of his Tarning</hi> Roman Catholick <hi>for Salvation.</hi> The <hi>2d</hi> Edition.</p>
            <p>A Diſcourſe concerning the Nature of Idolatry: In which the Biſhop of <hi>Oxford</hi>'s True and Only Notion of Idolatry is Conſidered and Confuted. 40.</p>
            <p>A Preſervative againſt Popery: Being ſome Plain Directions to Unlearn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Proteſtants, how to Diſpute with <hi>Romiſh</hi> Prieſts. The Firſt Part. By <hi>William Sherlock,</hi> D. D. The 4th Edition.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
